- I think it's possible
that physics has exploits
and we should be trying to find them.
Arranging some kind of a crazy
quantum mechanical system
that somehow gives you buffer overflow,
somehow gives you a rounding
error in the floating point.
Synthetic intelligence is kind of like
the next stage of development.
And I dunno where it
leads to, at some point
I suspect the universe
is some kind of a puzzle.
These synthetic AIs will uncover
that puzzle and solve it.
- The following is a conversation
with Andrej Karpathy,
previously the director of AI at Tesla.
And before that, at OpenAi and Stanford.
He is one of the greatest
scientists, engineers,
and educators in the history
of artificial intelligence.
This is the Lex Fridman Podcast.
To support it, please
check out our sponsors.
And now, dear friends,
here's Andrej Karpathy.
What is a neural network
and why does it seem to do
such a surprisingly good job of learning?
- What is a neural network?
It's a mathematical
abstraction of the brain.
I would say that's how it
was originally developed.
At the end of the day, it's
a mathematical expression
and it's a fairly simple
mathematical expression
when you get down to it.
It's basically a sequence
of meter multipliers,
whichever really dot
products mathematically
and some nonlinearity is thrown in.
And so it's a very simple
mathematical expression
and it's got knobs in it.
- Many knobs.
And these knobs are loosely
related to basically
the synapses in your brain.
They're trainable.
They're modifiable.
And so the idea is we
need to find the setting
of the knobs that makes the neural net
do whatever you want it to do,
like classify images and so on.
And so there's not too much
mystery I would say in it.
You might think that, basically,
you don't want to endow it
with too much meaning
with respect to the brain
and how it works.
It's really just a complicated
mathematical expression
with knobs.
And those knobs need a proper setting
for it to do something desirable.
- Yeah.
But poetry is just the collection
of letters with spaces,
but it can make us feel a certain way.
And in that same way,
when you get a large
number of knobs together,
whether it's inside the
brain or inside a computer,
they seem to surprise us with their power.
- Yeah.
I think that's fair.
So basically, I think I'm
underselling it by a lot
because you definitely do get
very surprising emergent
behaviors out of these neural nets
when they're large enough
and trained on complicated
enough problems.
Like say, for example,
the next-word prediction
in a massive dataset from the internet.
And then these neural nets take on
pretty surprising magical properties.
Yeah, I think it's kind of
interesting how much you can get
out of even very simple
mathematical formalism.
- When your brain right now is talking,
is it doing next-word prediction
or is it doing something more interesting?
- Well, it's definitely some
kind of a generative model
that's GPT like and prompted by you.
- [Lex] Yes.
- So you're giving me a prompt
and I'm kind of like responding
to it in a generative way.
- And by yourself perhaps a little bit,
like are you adding extra
prompts from your own memory
inside your head or no?
- Well, it definitely feels
like you're referencing
some kind of a declarative structure
of memory and so on.
And then you're putting that
together with your prompt
and giving away some answers.
- How much of what you just said
has been said by you before.
- Nothing, basically right?
- No, but if you actually
look at all the words
you've ever said in your
life and you do a search,
you'll probably have said
a lot of the same words
in the same order before.
- Yeah.
Could be.
I mean, I'm using phrases
that are common, et cetera,
but I'm remixing it into
a pretty unique sentence
at the end of the day.
But you're right, definitely,
there's like a ton of remixing.
- It's like Magnus Carlson
said I'm rated 2,900, whatever,
which is pretty decent.
I think you're talking very,
you're not giving enough credit
to neural nets here.
What's your best intuition
about this emergent behavior?
- I mean, it's kind of interesting
because I'm simultaneously
underselling them,
but I also feel like there's
an element to which I'm over-
it's actually kind of incredible
that you can get so much
emergent magical behavior
out of them despite them being
so simple mathematically.
So I think those are two
surprising statements
that are juxtaposed together.
And I think, basically, what it is,
is we are actually fairly good
at optimizing these neural nets.
And when you give them
a hard enough problem,
they are forced to learn
very interesting solutions
in the optimization.
And those solutions basically
have these emergent properties
that are very interesting.
- There's wisdom and
knowledge in the knobs.
- [Andrej] Yes.
- And so this representation
that's in the knobs
does it make sense to you intuitively,
that a large number of knobs
can hold a representation
that captures some deep wisdom
about the data it has looked at.
It's a lot of knobs.
- It's a lot of knobs.
And somehow, so speaking
concretely, one of the neural nets
that people are very excited
about right now are GPTs,
which are basically just
next-word prediction networks.
So you consume a sequence
of words from the internet
and you try to predict the next word.
And once you train these
on a large enough data set,
you can basically prompt these neural nets
in arbitrary ways and you can
ask them to solve problems.
And they will.
So you can just tell them,
you can make it look like
you're trying to solve some
kind of a mathematical problem.
And they will continue what
they think is the solution
based on what they've
seen on the internet.
And very often those solutions
look very remarkably consistent.
Look correct, potentially even.
- Do you still think about
the brain side of it?
So as neural nets as an abstraction,
a mathematical abstraction of the brain,
do you still draw wisdom
from the biological neural networks
or even the bigger question.
So you're a big fan of biology
and biological computation.
What impressive thing
is biology doing to you
that computers are not yet, that gap?
- I would say I'm definitely on,
I'm much more hesitant with
the analogies to the brain
than I think you would see
potentially in the field.
And I feel like certainly, the
way neural networks started
is everything stemmed from
inspiration by the brain.
But at the end of the day,
the artifacts that you get
after training, they are arrived at
by a very different optimization process
than the optimization process
that gave rise to the brain.
And so I think of it as a very
complicated alien artifact.
It's something different.
- [Lex] The brain?
- Oh no, sorry.
The neural nest that we're training.
- [Lex] Okay.
- They are a complicated alien artifact.
I do not make analogies to the brain
because I think the optimization process
that gave rise to it is very
different from the brain.
So there was no multi-agent,
self-play setup and evolution.
It was an optimization that is basically
what amounts to a compression objective
on a mass amount of data.
- Okay.
So artificial neural networks
are doing compression
and biological neural networks-
- [Andrej] Are trying to survive.
- Are not really doing
anything, they're an agent
in a multi-agent, self-play system
that's been running for
a very, very long time.
- Yes.
That said, evolution has
found that it is very useful
to predict and have a
predictive model in the brain.
And so, I think our
brain utilizes something
that looks like that as a part of it,
but it has a lot more catches and gizmos
and value functions and ancient nuclei
that are all trying to
like make it survive
and reproduce and everything else.
- And the whole thing through
embryogenesis is built
from a single-cell.
I mean, it's just the
code is inside the DNA
and it just builds it up
like the entire organism
with arms-
- [Andrej] It's definitely crazy.
- And the head and legs.
- [Andrej] Yes.
- And it does it pretty well.
- [Andrej] It should not be possible.
- So there's some learning going on.
There's some kind of computation
going through that building process.
I mean, I don't know where,
if you were just to look
at the entirety of
history of life on earth,
where do you think is the
most interesting invention?
Is it the origin of life itself?
Is it just jumping to Eukaryotes?
Is it mammals?
Is it humans themselves, Homo sapiens?
The origin of intelligence or
highly complex intelligence?
Or is it all just a continuation
of the same kind of process?
- Certainly, I would say it's
an extremely remarkable story
that I'm only briefly
learning about recently
all the way from, actually,
you almost have to start
at the formation of earth
and all of its conditions
and the entire solar system
and how everything is arranged
with Jupiter and moon and the
habitable zone and everything.
And then you have an active earth
that's turning over material
and then you start with a
biogenesis and everything.
And so it's all a pretty remarkable story.
I'm not sure that I can pick
a single unique piece of it
that I find most interesting.
I guess for me, as an artificial
intelligence researcher,
it's probably the last piece.
We have lots of animals
that are not building
technological society but we do.
And it seems to have
happened very quickly.
It seems to have happened very recently.
And something very
interesting happened there
that I don't fully understand.
I almost understand everything
else I think intuitively,
but I don't understand exactly that part
and how quick it was.
- Both explanations would be interesting.
One is that this is just a continuation
of the same kind of process.
There's nothing special about humans.
Deeply understanding that
would be very interesting
that we think of ourselves as special.
But it was obvious, it was
already written in the code
that you would have greater
and greater intelligence emerging.
And then the other explanation,
which is something truly special happened,
something like a rare event,
whether it's like crazy rare
event like a "Space Odyssey",
what would it be?
See if you say like the invention of fire
or as Richard Rankin says,
the beta males deciding
a clever way to kill the
alpha males by collaborating.
So just optimizing the
collaboration, the multi-agent,
aspect of the multi-agent and
that really being constrained
on resources and trying to
survive the collaboration aspect
is what created the complex intelligence.
But it seems like it's a natural algorithm
to the evolution process.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- What could possibly be a
magical thing that happened,
like a rare thing that would
say that humans are actually,
human-level intelligence is
actually a really rare thing
in the universe?
- Yeah, I'm hesitant to say
that it is rare by the way,
but it definitely seems like
it's like a punctuated
equilibrium where you have
lots of exploration and
then you have certain leaps,
sparse leaps in between.
So of course, like origin
of life would be one,
DNA, sex, Eukaryotic life,
the endosymbiosis event
where the archon ate little
bacteria, just the whole thing.
And then of course, emergence
of consciousness and so on.
So it seems like definitely
there are sparse events
where massive amount of progress was made.
But yeah, it's kind of hard to pick one.
- So you don't think humans are unique?
To that I ask you how many
intelligent alien civilizations
do you think are out there
and is their intelligence
different or similar to ours?
- Yeah, I've been preoccupied
with this question
quite a bit recently.
Basically, the Fermi paradox
and just thinking through.
And the reason actually
that I am very interested
in the origin of life is
fundamentally trying to understand
how common it is that there
are technological societies
out there in space.
And the more I study it,
the more I think that
there should be quite a few, quite a lot.
- Why haven't we heard from them?
'Cause I agree with you.
It feels like, I just don't see why
what we did here on earth
is so difficult to do.
- Yeah.
And especially when you
get into the details of it.
I used to think origin of life was very,
it was this magical rare event.
But then you read books
like for example Nick Lane,
"The Vital Question", "Life
Ascending", et cetera.
And he really gets in and
he really makes you believe
that this is not that rare.
- Basic chemistry.
- You have an active earth and
you have your alkaline vents
and you have lots of
alkaline waters mixing
where there is a devotion and
you have your proton gradients
and you have these little porous pockets
of these alkaline vents
that concentrate chemistry.
And basically, as he steps through
all of these little pieces,
you start to understand
that actually this is not that crazy.
You could see this happen on other systems
and he really takes
you from just a geology
to primitive life.
And he makes it feel like this
is actually pretty plausible.
And also like the origin of
life was actually fairly fast
after formation of earth,
if I remember correctly,
just a few hundred million
years or something like that
after basically when it was
possible, life actually arose.
And so that makes me feel like
that is not the constraint,
that is not the limiting variable
and that life should
actually be fairly common.
And then where the drop-offs are
is very interesting to think about.
I currently think that there's
no major drop-offs basically.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And so there should
be quite a lot of life.
And basically, where
that brings me to then
is the only way to reconcile the fact
that we haven't found anyone and so on
is that we can't see them,
we can't observe them.
- Just a quick brief comment,
Nick Lane and a lot of
biologists I talk to,
they really seem to think
that the jump from bacteria
to more complex organisms
is the hardest jump.
- [Andrej] The Eukaryotic life, basically.
- Yeah.
I get it.
They're much more knowledgeable than me
about the intricacies of biology.
But that seems crazy
'cause how many single-cell
organisms are there?
And how much time you have
surely it's not that difficult.
And a billion years is not even that long
of a time really, just all these bacteria
under constrained
resources battling it out.
I'm sure they can invent more complex.
I don't understand.
It's like how to move from
a "Hello, World!" program
to invent a function
or something like that.
I don't-
- Yeah.
- Yeah, so I'm with you.
I just feel like I don't see
any, if the origin of life,
that would be my intuition,
that's the hardest thing.
But if that's not the hardest thing
'cause it happened so quickly,
then it's gotta be everywhere and yeah,
maybe we're just too dumb to see it.
- Well, it's just we don't
have really good mechanisms
for seeing this life.
So I'm not an expert just to preface this
but just from what-
- On aliens?
I wanna meet an expert
on alien intelligence
and how to communicate.
- I'm very suspicious of our ability
to find these intelligences out there
and to find these earths like radio waves,
for example, are terrible.
Their power drops off as
basically 1 over R-squared.
So I remember reading that
our current radio waves
would not be, the ones
that we are broadcasting,
would not be measurable by
our devices today only like,
was it like one 10th of a light year away?
Not even, basically, tiny distance
because you really need
like a targeted transmission
of massive power directed somewhere
for this to be picked
up on long distances.
And so I just think that our ability
to measure is not amazing.
I think there's probably
other civilizations out there.
And then the big question is
why don't they build one man probes
and why don't they interstellar travel
across the entire galaxy?
And my current answer is,
it's probably interstellar
travel is really hard.
You have the interstellar
medium if you wanna move
at close to speed of light,
you're going to be encountering
bullets along the way
because even like tiny hydrogen atoms
and little particles of dust
have massive kinetic energy
at those speeds.
And so, basically, you need
some kind of shielding,
you have all the cosmic radiation,
it's just brutal out there.
It's really hard.
And so my thinking is
maybe interstellar travel
is just extremely hard.
You have to learn slow.
- Like billions of years to build hard?
It feels like we're not
a billion years away
from doing that.
- It just might be that it's very,
you have to go very slowly potentially,
as an example, through space.
- Right.
As opposed to close to the speed of light.
- Yeah.
So I'm suspicious basically
of our ability to measure life
and I'm suspicious of the
ability to just permeate
all of space in the
galaxy or across galaxies.
And that's the only way
that I can currently see away around it.
- Yeah, it's kind of mind-blowing
to think that there's
trillions of intelligent
alien civilizations out there
slowly traveling through space.
- [Andrej] Maybe.
- To meet each other.
And some of them meet,
some of them go to war,
some of them collaborate.
- Or they're all just independent.
They're all just like little pockets.
I don't know.
- Well, statistically if
there's trillions of them,
surely some of them,
some of the pockets are
close enough together.
- Some of them happen to be close.
Yeah.
- And close enough to see each other.
See, once you see something
that is definitely complex
life, if we see something.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- We're probably going to be
intensely aggressively motivated
to figure out what the hell
that is and try to meet them.
But what would be your
first instinct, to try to,
at a generational-level, meet
them or defend against them?
Or what would be your
instinct as a president
of the United States and a scientist?
I don't know which hat you
prefer in this question.
- Yeah, I think the
question, it's really hard.
I will say like for example, for us,
we have lots of primitive life
forms on earth next to us.
We have all kinds of
ants and everything else
and we share a space with
them and we are hesitant
to impact on them and we're
trying to protect them
by default, because they are amazing,
interesting dynamical systems
that took a long time to evolve.
And they are interesting and special
and I don't know that you
wanna destroy that by default.
And so I like complex dynamical systems
that took a lot of time to evolve.
I think I'd like to preserve
it if I can afford to.
And I'd like to think that
the same would be true
about the galactic resources
and that they would think
that we're kind of
incredible interesting story
that took time, it took a
few billing years to unravel
and you don't want to just destroy it.
- I could see two aliens
talking about earth right now
and saying I'm a big fan of
complex dynamical systems.
So I think it was a
value to preserve these
and who basically are
a video game they watch
or show, a TV show that they watch.
- Yeah.
I think you would need
like a very good reason
I think to destroy it.
Why don't we destroy
these end farms and so on?
It's because we're not actually
really in direct competition
with them right now.
We do it accidentally and so on,
but there's plenty of resources.
And so why would you destroy something
that is so interesting and precious?
- Well, from a scientific
perspective you might probe it.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- You might interact with it lightly.
- Exactly.
You might wanna learn something from it.
Right.
- So I wonder, there could
be certain physical phenomena
that we think is a physical phenomena,
but it's actually interacting with us
to poke the finger and see what happens.
- Yeah.
I think it should be very
interesting to scientists,
other alien scientists, what happened here
and what we're seeing today is a snapshot,
basically, it's a result of
a huge amount of computation
of over billion years
or something like that.
- It could have been initiated by aliens.
This could be a computer
running a program.
Okay.
If you had the power to
do this wouldn't you-
Okay, for sure.
At least I would, I would
pick an earth-like planet
that has the conditions,
base my understanding
of the chemistry prerequisites for life.
And I would seed it with
life and run it, right?
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Wouldn't you 100% do that and observe it
and then protect?
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- I mean that's not just
a hell of a good TV show.
It's a good scientific experiment.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- And it's physical simulation.
Right.
Maybe, evolution is the
most, actually running it,
is the most efficient way
to understand computation
or to compute stuff.
- Or to understand life
or what life looks like
and what branches it can take.
- It does make me kind of feel weird
that we're part of a science experiment,
but maybe everything's
a science experiment,
does that change anything for us,
if we're a science experiment?
- [Andrej] I don't know.
- Two descendants of apes talking about
being inside of a science experiment.
- I'm suspicious of this idea
of a deliberate panspermia
as you described it, sort of.
- Yes.
- I don't see a divine
intervention in some way
in the historical record right now.
I do feel like the story in these books,
like Nick Lane's books and so on,
sort of makes sense and it
makes sense how life arose
on earth uniquely.
And yeah, I don't need to reach
for more exotic explanations right now.
- Sure.
But NPCs inside a video game,
don't observe any divine
intervention either.
We might just be all NPCs
running a kind of code.
- Maybe eventually they will,
currently, NPCs are really dumb.
But once they're running
GPTs, maybe they will be like,
"Hey, this is really suspicious.
What the hell?"
- So you famously Tweeted,
"It looks like if you
bombard earth with photons
for a while, you can emit a Roadster."
So if like in "Hitchhiker's
Guide to the Galaxy",
we would summarize the story of earth.
So in that book it's mostly harmless.
What do you think is all
the possible stories,
a paragraph long or sentence long
that earth could be summarized as,
once it's done it's computation?
So all the possible full,
if earth is a book, right?
- Yeah.
- Probably there has to be an ending.
I mean there's going to be an end to earth
and it could end in all kinds of ways.
It can end soon.
It can end later.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- What do you think are
the possible stories?
- Well definitely, there seems
to be, yeah, you're sort of,
it's pretty incredible that
these self-replicating systems
will basically arise from the dynamics
and then they perpetuate
themselves and become more complex
and eventually, become
conscious and build a society.
And I feel like in some sense
it's a deterministic wave
that just happens on any sufficiently
well-arranged system like earth.
And so I feel like there's a certain sense
of inevitability in it
and it's really beautiful.
- And it ends somehow, right?
So it's a chemically diverse environment
where complex dynamical systems can evolve
and become more, further,
and further complex.
But then there's a certain, what is it?
There's certain terminating conditions.
- Yeah.
I dunno what the
terminating conditions are,
but definitely, there's
a trend line of something
and we're part of that story.
And where does that, where does it go?
So, we're famously described often
as a biological boot loader for AIs
and that's because humans,
I mean, we're an incredible
biological system
and we're capable of
computation and love and so on,
but we're extremely inefficient as well.
We're talking to each other through audio.
It's just embarrassing honestly
that we're manipulating like
seven symbols, serially,
we're using vocal chords.
It's all happening over multiple seconds.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- It's just embarrassing
when you step down
to the frequencies at
which computers operate
or are able to cooperate on.
And so basically, it does seem
like synthetic intelligences
are the next stage of development.
And I dunno where it leads
to, at some point I suspect
the universe is some kind of a puzzle
and these synthetic AIs
will uncover that puzzle
and solve it.
- And then what happens after, right?
'Cause if you just like
fast forward earth,
many billions of years, it's
quiet and then it's turmoil,
you see city lights and stuff like that.
And then what happens at the end?
Is it a, or is it a
calming, is it explosion?
Is it like earth open like a giant.
'Cause you said emit Roadsters.
Will it start emitting a
giant number of satellites?
- Yeah.
Some kind of a crazy explosion.
And we're living, we're
stepping through a explosion
and we're living day-to-day
and it doesn't look like it.
But it's actually, I saw a
very cool animation of earth
and life on earth and,
basically, nothing happens
for a long time.
And then the last like two seconds,
basically cities and everything and just,
and the lower orbit just gets cluttered
and just the whole thing
happens in the last two seconds
and you're like, "This is exploding.
This is a state of explosion."
- Yeah, yeah.
If you play it a normal speed.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- It'll just look like an explosion.
- It's a firecracker.
We're living in a firecracker.
- Where it's going to start emitting
all kinds of interesting things.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- And then, so explosion doesn't-
it might actually look
like a little explosion
with lights and fire and energy emitted,
all that kind of stuff.
But when you look inside the
details of the explosion,
there's actual complexity
happening where there's like,
yeah, human life or some kind of life.
- We hope it's not a
destructive firecracker.
It's kind of like a
constructive firecracker.
- [Lex] All right.
So given that.
- I think-
- [Lex] Hilarious discussion.
- It is really interesting to think about
what the puzzle of the universe is.
Did the creator of the
universe give us a message?
For example in the book
"Contact", Carl Sagan,
there's a message for any
civilization in the digits
in the expansion of Pi
and base 11, eventually,
which is kind of an interesting thought.
Maybe we're supposed to be
giving a message to our creator,
maybe we're supposed to somehow create
some kind of a quantum mechanical system
that alerts them to our
intelligent presence here.
'Cause if you think about
it from their perspective,
it's just say like quantum field theory,
massive cellular automaton-like thing.
And how do you even notice that we exist?
You might not even be able to
pick us up in that simulation.
And so how do you prove that you exist,
that you're intelligent,
and that you're part of the universe?
- So this is like a touring test
for intelligence from earth.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- I mean maybe this is
like trying to complete
the next word in a sentence.
This is a complicated way of that.
earth is basically sending a message back.
- Yeah.
The puzzle is basically alerting
the creator that we exist.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- Or maybe the puzzle is
just to just break out
of the system and just stick
it to the creator in some way.
Basically, like if you're
playing a video game,
you can somehow find an exploit
and find a way to execute
on the host machine in arbitrary code.
For example, I believe
someone got a game of Mario
to play pong just by exploiting it
and then basically writing
code and being able to execute
arbitrary code in the game.
And so maybe we should be,
maybe that's the puzzle
is that we should find
a way to exploit it.
So, I think like some
of these synthetic AIs
will eventually find the universe
to be some kind of a puzzle
and then solve it in some way.
And that's kind of like
the end game somehow.
- Do you often think
about it as a simulation?
So as are the universe
being a kind of computation
that might have bugs and exploits?
- Yes.
Yeah, I think so.
- [Lex] Is that what
physics is, essentially?
- I think it's possible
that physics has exploits
and we should be trying to find them.
Arranging some kind of a crazy
quantum mechanical system
that somehow gives you buffer overflow
somehow gives you a rounding
error and the floating point.
- Yeah, that's right.
And more and more sophisticated
exploits, those are jokes,
but that could be actually
very close to reality.
- Yeah.
We'll find some way to
extract infinite energy.
For example, when you train
reinforcement learning agents
in physical simulations and you
ask them to say, run quickly
on the flat ground, they'll end up doing
all kinds of weird things
in part of that optimization, right?
They'll get on their back leg
and they'll slide across the floor.
And it's because the optimization,
the enforcement learning
optimization on that agent
has figured out a way to
extract infinite energy
from the friction forces
and, basically, their poor implementation.
And they found a way to
generate infinite energy
and just slide across the surface.
And it's not what you expected,
it's sort of like a perverse solution.
And so maybe we can find
something like that.
Maybe we can be that little dog
in this physical simulation.
- That cracks or escapes
the intended consequences
of the physics that the
universe came up with.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- We'll figure out some kind
of shortcut to some weirdness.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- And then, oh man, but see
the problem with that weirdness
is the first person to
discover the weirdness,
like sliding on the back legs,
that's all we're gonna do.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- It's very quickly become
everybody does that thing.
So the paperclip maximizer
is a ridiculous idea,
but that very well could be
what then we'll just all switch
to that 'cause it's so fun.
- Well, no person will discover
it, I think by the way,
I think it's going to have to be
some kind of a super-intelligent
AGI of a third generation.
We're building the
first-generation AGI, maybe.
- Third generation.
Yeah.
So the boot loader for an AI,
that AI will be a boot
loader for another AI.
- [Andrej] Better Ai.
Yeah.
- And then there's no
way for us to introspect
what that might even.
- I think it's very
likely that these things,
for example, say you have these AGIs,
it's very likely for example,
they will be completely inert.
I like these kinds of
sci-fi books sometimes
where these things are
just completely inert,
they don't interact with anything.
And I find that kind of beautiful
because they've probably
figured out the meta-game
of the universe in some way, potentially.
They're doing something
completely beyond our imagination
and they don't interact with
simple chemical life forms.
Why would you do that?
So I find those kinds of ideas compelling.
- What's their source of fun?
What are they doing?
What's the source of pleasure?
- Well, probably
puzzle-solving in the universe?
- But inert, so can you
define what it means inert?
So they escape the interaction
with physical reality?
- They will appear inert to us, as in
they will behave in some
very strange way to us
because they're beyond,
they're playing the meta-game.
And the meta-game is probably say,
like arranging quantum mechanical systems
in some very weird ways to
extract infinite energy,
solve the digital expansion
of Pi to whatever amount,
they will build their own
little fusion reactors
or something crazy.
They're doing something
beyond comprehension
and not understandable to us
and actually brilliant under the hood.
- What if quantum mechanics
itself is the system
and we're just thinking it's physics
but we're really parasites
on or not parasite.
We're not really hurting physics,
we're just living on this organism
and we're like trying to understand it.
But really it is an
organism and with a deep,
deep intelligence maybe
physics itself is the organism
that's doing the super interesting thing
and we're just like one little thing.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Ant sitting on top of it
trying to get energy from it.
- Yeah.
We're just like these
particles in the wave
that I feel like is mostly deterministic
and takes universe from
some kind of a big bang
to some kind of a
super-intelligent replicator,
some kind of a stable
point in the universe
given these laws of physics.
- You don't think, as Einstein
said, God doesn't play dice?
So you think it's mostly deterministic?
There's no randomness in the thing?
- I think it's deterministic.
Oh, there's tons of,
well, I'm gonna be careful
with randomness.
- [Lex] Pseudo-random?
- Yeah, I don't like random.
I think maybe the laws of
physics are deterministic.
Yeah, I think they're deterministic.
- You just got really
uncomfortable with the question.
Do you have anxiety about
whether the universe
is random or not?
Is it a source?
- [Andrej] There's no randomness, no.
- You said you like "Good Will Hunting".
It's not your fault Andrej.
It's not your fault, man.
So you don't like the randomness?
- Yeah, I think it's unsettling.
I think it's a deterministic system.
I think that things that look random,
like say the collapse of the
wave function, et cetera,
I think they're actually deterministic,
just entanglement and so on
and some kind of a multiverse
theory something, something.
- Okay.
So why does it feel like
we have a free will?
Like if I raise this hand,
I chose to do this now.
That doesn't feel like
a deterministic thing.
It feels like I'm making a choice.
- [Andrej] It feels like it.
- Okay.
So it's all feelings.
It's just feelings.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
So when our RL agent is
making a choice is that,
it's not really making a choice,
the choice was already there.
- Yeah.
You're interpreting the choice
and you're creating a narrative
for having made it.
- Yeah.
And now we're talking about the narrative,
it's very meta.
Looking back, what is the most beautiful
or surprising idea in deep
learning or AI in general
that you've come across?
You've seen this field explode
and grow in interesting ways.
Just what cool ideas, like
what made you sit back and go
hmm, big or small?
- Well, the one that I've
been thinking about recently
the most probably is the
transformer architecture.
So basically, neural networks
have a lot of architectures
that were trendy have come and gone
for different sensory modalities.
Like for vision, audio,
text, you would process them
with different-looking neural nets.
And recently, we've seen this convergence
towards one architecture, the transformer
and you can feed it video,
or you can feed it images,
or speech or text and
it just gobbles it up.
And it's a bit of a
general-purpose computer
that is also trainable
and very efficient to run
in our hardware.
And so this paper came
out in 2016, I wanna say.
- [Lex] "Attention is all you need".
- "Attention is all you need".
- You criticized the
paper title in retrospect
that it wasn't, it didn't
foresee the bigness
of the impact that it was going to have.
- Yeah.
I'm not sure if the authors
were aware of the impact
that that paper would go on to have.
Probably they weren't but
I think they were aware
of some of the motivations
and design decisions
behind the transformer and
they chose not to, I think,
expand on it in that way in the paper.
And so I think they had an
idea that there was more
than just the surface of just like,
oh, we're just doing translation
and here's a better architecture.
You're not just doing translation.
This is like a really cool
differentiable, optimizable,
efficient computer that you've proposed.
And maybe they didn't
have all of that foresight
but I think it's really interesting.
- Isn't it funny, sorry to interrupt,
that that title is
memeable, that they went
for such a profound idea.
I don't think anyone used that
kind of title before, right?
- "Attention is all you need"?
Yeah.
It's like a meme or something, basically.
- Yeah.
Isn't it funny that when, maybe if it was
a more serious title it
wouldn't have the impact.
- Honestly, yeah, there
is an element of me
that honestly agrees with
you and prefers it this way.
- [Lex] Yes.
- If it was too grand
it would over-promise
and then under-deliver potentially.
So you want to just meme
your way to greatness?
- That should be a T-shirt.
So you Tweeted, "The
Transformer is a magnificent
neural network architecture
because it is a general-purpose
differentiable computer.
It is simultaneously
expressive in the forward pass,
optimizable via back-propagation
gradient dissent,
and efficient high
parallelism compute graph."
Can you discuss some of those details,
Expressive, optimizable, efficient?
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- From memory or in general,
whatever comes to your heart.
- You want to have a
general-purpose computer
that you can train on arbitrary problems
like say the task of next-work prediction
or detecting if there's a cat in a image
or something like that.
And you want to train this computer
so you want to set its weights.
And I think there's
number of design criteria
that overlap in the
transformer simultaneously
that made it very successful.
And I think the authors
were deliberately trying to
make this really powerful architecture.
And so basically, it's very
powerful in the forward pass
because it's able to express
very general computation
as something that looks
like message passing.
You have nodes and they all store vectors
and these nodes get to
basically look at each other,
each other's vectors and
they get to communicate
and basically, nodes get to broadcast,
"Hey, I'm looking for certain things."
And then other nodes get to broadcast,
"Hey, these are the things I have."
Those are the keys and the values.
- So it's not just attention.
- Yeah, exactly.
Transformer is much more than
just the attention component.
It's got many pieces,
architectural that went into it,
the residual connection,
the way it's arranged,
there's a multilayer perceptron
and they are the way
it's stacked and so on.
But basically, there's
a message-passing scheme
where nodes get to look at each other,
decide what's interesting,
and then update each other.
And so I think when you
get to the details of it,
I think it's a very expressive function
so it can express lots of
different types of algorithms
in a forward pass.
Not only that but the way it's designed
with the residual connections,
layer normalizations,
the Softmax, attention, and everything,
it's also optimizable.
This is a really big deal
because there's lots of computers
that are powerful that you can't optimize
or that are not easy to optimize
using the techniques that we have,
which is back-propagation
and gradient descent,
these are first-order methods,
very simple optimizers really.
And so you also need it to be optimizable.
And then lastly, you want
it to run efficiently
in our hardware.
Our hardware is a massive
throughput machine like GPUs,
they prefer lots of parallelism.
So you don't want to do lots
of sequential operations,
you want to do a lot
of operations serially
and the transformer is designed
with that in mind as well.
And so it's designed for our hardware
and is designed to both be very expressive
in a forward pass, but
also very optimizable
in the backward pass.
- And you said that the
residual connection support,
an ability to learn short
algorithms fast and first
and then gradually extend
them longer during training.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- What's the idea of
learning short algorithms?
- Right.
Think of it as a, so
basically a transformer
is a series of blocks, right?
And these blocks have attention
and a little multilayer perceptron,
and so you go off into a
block and you come back
to this residual pathway
and then you go off
and you come back and then you have
a number of layers arranged sequentially.
And so the way to look at it I think is
because of the residual
pathway in the backward pass,
the gradients sort of flow
along it uninterrupted
because addition distributes
the gradient equally
to all of its branches.
So the gradient from the
supervision at the top
just floats directly to the first layer.
And all these residual
connections are arranged
so that in the beginning,
during initialization,
they contribute nothing
to the residual pathway.
So what it looks like is,
imagine the transformer
is like a Python function, like a def,
and you get to do various lines of code.
Say you have a hundred
layers-deep transformer,
typically they would be
much shorter, say 20.
So you have 20 lines of code
then you can do something in them.
And so think of, during the optimization
basically what it looks
like is first you optimize
the first line of code, and
then the second line of code
can kick in, and the third
line of code can kick in.
And I feel like because
of the residual pathway
and the dynamics of the optimization,
you can sort of learn
a very short algorithm
that gets the approximate answer,
but then the other layers
can sort of kick in
and start to create a contribution.
And at the end of it you're
optimizing over an algorithm
that is 20 lines of code.
Except these lines of
code are very complex
because it's an entire
block of a transformer.
You can do a lot in there.
Well, what's really interesting
is that this transformer
architecture actually
has been remarkably resilient.
Basically, the transformer
that came out in 2016
is the transformer you would use today
except you reshuffle
some of the layer norms.
The layer normalizations
have been reshuffled
to a prenorm formulation and
so it's been remarkably stable
but there's a lot of bells and whistles
that people have attached
on it and try to improve it.
I do think that basically, it's a big step
in simultaneously optimizing
for lots of properties
of a desirable neural
network architecture.
And I think people have
been trying to change it
but it's proven remarkably resilient.
But I do think that there should be
even better architectures potentially.
- But you admire the resilience here?
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- There's something profound
about this architecture
that leads to resilience.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- So maybe everything can
be turned into a problem
that transformers can solve.
- Currently, definitely
looks like the transformers
taking over AI and you can feed basically
arbitrary problems into
it and it's a general
differentiable computer and
it's extremely powerful.
And this conversions in AI
has been really interesting
to watch for me personally.
- What else do you think
could be discovered here
about transformers?
Like what surprising
thing or is it a stable,
out in a stable place?
Is there something interesting
we might discover about transformers?
Like aha moments, maybe
has to do with memory,
maybe knowledge representation,
that kind of stuff.
- Definitely, the zeitgeist
today is just pushing,
basically, right now the zeitgeist
is do not touch the transformer.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- Touch everything else.
- [Lex] Yes.
- So people are scaling up the data sets,
making them much, much bigger.
They're working on the evaluation,
making the evaluation much, much bigger.
And they're basically keeping
the architecture unchanged.
And that's how we've,
that's the last five years
of progress in AI.
- What do you think
about one flavor of it,
which is language models?
Have you been surprised,
has your imagination
been captivated by, you
mentioned GPT and all the bigger,
and bigger, and bigger language models
and what are the limits of
those models do you think?
So just for the task of natural language.
- Basically, the way
GPT is trained, right,
is you've just download a
massive amount of text data
from the internet and you
try to predict the next word
in a sequence, roughly
speaking you're predicting
little word chunks but
roughly speaking that's it.
And what's been really
interesting to watch is
basically, it's a language model.
Language models have actually
existed for a very long time.
There's papers on language
modeling from 2003, even earlier.
- Can you explain in that
case, what a language model is?
- Yeah, so language model,
just basically the rough idea
is just predicting the
next word in a sequence,
roughly speaking.
So there's a paper from, for
example, Bengio and the team
from 2003, where for the
first time they were using
a neural network to take
say like three or five words
and predict the next word.
And they're doing this
on much smaller data sets
and the neural net is not a transformer,
it's a multilayer perceptron
but it's the first time
that a neural network has
been applied in that setting.
But even before neural networks
there were language models
except they were using n-gram models.
So n-gram models are
just count-based models.
So if you try to take two
words and predict a third one,
you just count up how
many times you've seen
any two-word combinations
and what came next.
And what you predict as coming next
is just what you've seen the
most of in the training set.
And so language modeling has
been around for a long time.
Neural networks have done
language modeling for a long time.
So really what's new or
interesting or exciting
is just realizing that
when you scale it up
with a powerful enough
neural net, a transformer,
you have all these emergent properties
where basically what happens is
if you have a large
enough data set of text,
you are in the task of
predicting the next word.
You are multitasking a huge amount
of different kinds of problems.
You are multitasking,
understanding of chemistry,
physics, human nature, lots
of things are clustered
in that objective.
It's a very simple objective but actually,
you have to understand
a lot about the world
to make that prediction.
- You just said the U word
understanding, are you,
in terms of chemistry,
and physics, and so on,
what do you feel like it's doing?
Is it searching for the right context in,
what is the actual process happening here?
- Yeah, so basically,
it gets a thousand words
and it's trying to predict
a thousand and first.
And in order to do that very, very well
over the entire data set
available on the internet,
you actually have to basically
understand the context
of what's going on in there.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And it's a sufficiently hard problem
that if you have a
powerful enough computer,
like a transformer, you end
up with interesting solutions.
And you can ask it to
do all kinds of things
and it shows a lot of emergent properties
like in-context learning,
that was the big deal with GPT
and the original paper
when they published it,
is that you can just
prompt it in various ways
and ask it to do various things
and it will just kind of
complete the sentence.
But in the process of just
completing the sentence
it's actually solving all
really interesting problems
that we care about.
- Do you think it's doing
something like understanding,
like when we use the word
understanding for us humans?
- I think it's doing some understanding,
in its weights it understands
I think a lot about the world
and it has to in order
to predict the next word
in a sequence.
- So it's trained on the
data from the internet.
What do you think about this
approach in terms of data sets,
of using data from the internet?
Do you think the internet
has enough structured data
to teach AI about human civilization?
- Yeah, so I think the internet
has a huge amount of data.
I'm not sure if it's
a complete enough set.
I dunno that text is enough for having
a sufficiently powerful AGI as an outcome.
- Of course, there is audio,
and video, and images,
and all that kind of stuff.
- Yeah.
So text by itself I'm a
little bit suspicious about,
there's a ton of things we
don't put in text, in writing
just because they're obvious
to us about how the world works
and the physics of it
and that things fall.
We don't put that stuff in
text because why would you,
we share that understanding.
And so text is a communication
medium between humans
and it's not a all-encompassing
medium of knowledge
about the world.
But as you pointed out, we do have video,
and we have images, and we have audio.
And so I think that
definitely helps a lot.
But we haven't trained models sufficiently
across all those modalities yet.
So I think that's what a lot
of people are interested in.
- But I wonder what that
shared understanding
of what we might call common sense
has to be learned, inferred
in order to complete
the sentence correctly.
So maybe the fact that it's
implied on the internet
the model's gonna have to learn that
not by reading about it, by inferring it
in the representation.
So common sense, just like we,
I don't think we learn common
sense, like nobody says,
tells us explicitly, we
just figure it all out
by interacting with the world.
- [Andrej] Right.
- And so here's a model of reading about
the way people interact with the world.
It might have to infer that.
I wonder.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- You briefly worked on a
project called World of Bits,
training an RL system to
take actions on the internet
versus just consuming the
internet like we talked about.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Do you think there's a
future for that kind of system
interacting with the internet
to help the learning?
- Yes.
I think that's probably the final frontier
for a lot of these models,
so as you mentioned,
when I was at OpenAI,
I was working on this
project World of Bits
and basically, it was the
idea of giving neural networks
access to a keyboard and a mouse.
And the idea is that-
- What could possibly go wrong?
- So basically, you perceive
the input of the screen pixels
and basically, the state of
the computer is visualized
for human consumption in
images of the web browser
and stuff like that.
And then you give the
neural network the ability
to press keyboards and use the mouse
and we're trying to
get it to, for example,
complete bookings and
interact with user interfaces.
And-
- What'd you learn from that experience?
Like what was some fun stuff?
'Cause, that's a super cool idea.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- I mean it's like, yeah, I mean
the step between observer to actor.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Is a super fascinating step.
- Yeah.
Well, it's the universal interface
in the digital realm, I would say.
And there's a universal
interface in the physical realm,
which in my mind is a humanoid
form factor kind of thing.
We can later talk about
optimist and so on,
but I feel like they're a
similar philosophy in some way
where the physical world is
designed for the human form
and the digital world is
of seeing the screen and
using keyboard and mouse.
And so it's the universal interface
that can basically command
the digital infrastructure
we've built up for ourselves.
And so it feels like a very
powerful interface to command
and to build on top of.
Now, to your question as to
what I learned from that,
it's interesting because the World of Bits
was basically too early I
think at OpenAI, at the time.
This is around 2015 or so.
And the zeitgeist at that
time was very different in AI
from the zeitgeist today.
At the time everyone was super excited
about reinforcement learning from scratch.
This is the time of the Atari paper
where neural networks
were playing Atari games
and beating humans in some
cases, AlphaGo, and so on.
So everyone's very excited
about training neural
networks from scratch,
using reinforcement learning directly.
It turns out that reinforcement learning
is extremely inefficient way
of training neural networks
because you're taking all these actions
and all these observations
and you get some sparse
rewards once in a while.
So you do all this stuff
based on all these inputs
and once in a while you're
told you did a good thing,
you did a bad thing and it's
just an extremely hard problem,
you can't learn from that.
You can burn a forest and you
can brute force through it.
And we saw that I think
with Go and Dota and so on,
and it does work, but
it's extremely inefficient
and not how you want to approach problems,
practically speaking.
And so that's the
approach that at the time
we also took to World of Bits.
We would have an agent
initialize randomly,
so he would keyboard mash, and mouse mash,
and try to make a booking.
And it just revealed the insanity
of that approach very quickly,
where you have to stumble
by the correct booking
in order to get a reward
of you did it correctly.
And you're never gonna stumble
by it by chance at random.
- So even with a simple web interface
there's too many options.
- There's just too many options
and it's two spars of a reward signal.
And you're starting
from scratch at the time
and so you don't know how to read,
you don't understand
pictures, images, buttons.
You don't understand what
it means to make a booking.
But now what's happened is
it is time to revisit that
and OpenAi is interested in this,
companies like Adept are
interested in this, and so on.
And the idea is coming
back because the interface
is very powerful but
now you're not training
an agent from scratch.
You are taking the GPT
as an initialization.
So GPT is pre-trained on all of text
and it understands what's a booking,
it understands what's a submit,
it understands quite a bit more.
And so it already has
those representations.
They are very powerful and
that makes all the training
significantly more efficient
and makes the problem tractable.
- Should the interaction
be the way humans see it,
with the buttons and the language,
or should it be with the
HTML, JavaScript, and the CSS?
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- What do you think is the better?
- So today all this interaction
is mostly on the level
of HTML, CSS, and so on.
That's done because of
computational constraints.
But I think ultimately,
everything is designed
for human visual consumption
and so at the end of the day
there's all the additional
information is in the layout
of the webpage, and what's next to you,
and what's a red background,
and all this kind of stuff.
And what it looks like visually.
So I think that's the final frontier
is we are taking in pixels
and we're giving out keyboard,
mouse commands, but I think
it's impractical still today.
- Do you worry about bots on
the internet given these ideas,
given how exciting they are?
Do you worry about bots on
Twitter being not the stupid bots
that we see now with the crypto bots,
but the bots that might
be out there actually
that we don't see, that
they're interacting
in interesting ways.
So this kind of system
feels like it should be able
to pass the, I'm not a robot
click button, whatever.
Do you actually understand
how that test works?
I don't quite, there's
a checkbox or whatever
that you click.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- It's presumably tracking.
- [Andrej] Oh, I see.
- Like mouse movement
and the timing and so on.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- So exactly this kind of
system we're talking about
should be able to pass that.
So yeah.
What do you feel about bots
that are language models
plus have some interactability
and are able to Tweet
and reply and so on?
Do you worry about that world?
- Yeah, I think it's always
been a bit of an arms race
between the attack and the defense,
so the attack will get stronger
but the defense will get stronger as well.
Our ability to detect that.
- How do you defend, how do you detect,
how do you know that your Karpathy account
on Twitter is human?
How would you approach that,
like if people were to claim,
how would you defend
yourself in the court of law
that I'm a human, this account is human?
- Yeah, at some point I think it might be,
I think society will evolve a little bit.
We might start signing, digitally signing
some of our correspondence
or things that we create.
Right now it's not necessary
but maybe in the future, it might be.
I do think that we are
going towards the world
where we share the digital space with AIs.
- [Lex] Synthetic beings.
- Yeah.
And they will get much better
and they will share our digital realm
and they'll eventually share
our physical realm as well.
It's much harder but that's
kind of like the world
we're going towards.
And most of them will
be benign and helpful
and some of them will be malicious.
And it's going to be an arms
race trying to detect them.
- So, I mean the worst isn't the AIs,
the worst is the AIs
pretending to be human.
So, I don't know if it's always malicious.
There's obviously a lot
of malicious applications,
but it could also be if I was an AI
I would try very hard
to pretend to be human
because we're in a human world.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- I wouldn't get any respect as an AI.
- I wanna get some love and respect.
- I don't think the
problem is intractable.
People are thinking about
the proof of personhood.
- [Lex] Yes.
- And we might start
digitally signing our stuff
and we might all end up having like, yeah,
basically some solution
for proof of personhood.
It doesn't seem to me intractable,
it's just something that we
haven't had to do until now.
But I think once the need
really starts to emerge,
which is soon, I think people
will think about it much more.
- But that too will be
a race because obviously
you can probably spoof or
fake the proof of personhood.
So you have to try to figure out how to-
- [Andrej] Probably.
- I mean it's weird that we
have social security numbers,
and passports, and stuff.
It seems like it's harder to fake stuff
in the physical space.
But in the digital
space, it just feels like
it's gonna be very tricky.
Very tricky to out, 'cause it
seems to be pretty low cost
to fake stuff.
What are you gonna put an AI in jail
for trying to use a fake personhood proof?
I mean, okay, fine, you'll
put a lot of AIs in jail,
but there'll be more AIs,
like exponentially more.
The cost of creating a bot is very low
unless there's some kind
of way to track accurately.
Like you're not allowed
to create any program
without tying yourself to that program.
Any program that runs on the internet,
you'll be able to trace every
single human programming
that was involved with that program.
- [Andrej] Right.
Yeah.
Maybe you have to start declaring when,
we have to start drawing those boundaries
and keeping track of, okay,
what are digital entities
versus human entities
and what is the ownership
of human entities and digital entities
and something like that.
I don't know but I think I'm optimistic
that this is possible and in some sense
we're currently in the worst time of it
because all these bots suddenly
have become very capable
but we don't have defenses
yet built up as a society
but I think that doesn't
seem to me intractable,
it's just something that
we have to deal with.
- It seems weird that the Twitter bot,
like really crappy Twitter
bots, are so numerous.
- [Andrej] Yes.
- So I presume that the engineers
at Twitter are very good.
So it seems like what
I would infer from that
is it seems like a hard problem.
They're probably catching, alright,
if I were to sort of steel-man the case,
it's a hard problem
and there's a huge cost
to false positive to
removing a post by somebody
that's not a bot, that creates
a very bad user experience.
So they're very cautious about removing.
And maybe the bots are
really good at learning
what gets removed and not
such that they can stay ahead
of the removal process very quickly.
- My impression of it honestly,
is there's a lot of longing for it.
I mean.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- It's not subtle, is my impression of it.
It's not subtle.
- But you have, yeah, that's
my impression as well.
But it feels like maybe you're seeing
the tip of the iceberg,
maybe the number of
bots is in the trillions
and you have to like, just
it's a constant assault of bots
and you, I don't know, you
have to steel-man the case.
'Cause the bots I'm seeing
are pretty like obvious.
I could write a few lines of
code that catch these bots.
- Yeah.
I mean definitely, there's
a lot of longing for it.
But I will say I agree that if
you are a sophisticated actor
you could probably create
a pretty good bot right now
using tools like GPTs because
it's a language model.
You can generate faces
that look quite good now
and you can do this at scale.
And so I think, yeah, it's quite plausible
and it's going to be hard to defend.
- There was a Google engineer that claimed
that the LaMDA was sentient.
Do you think there's any inkling
of truth to what he felt?
And more importantly, to me at least,
do you think language models
will achieve sentience
or the illusion of sentience soonish?
- Yeah.
To me, it's a little bit of a
canary in a coal mine moment.
Honestly, a little bit because,
so this engineer spoke
to a chatbot at Google
and became convinced that
this bot is sentient.
- He asked it some existential
philosophical questions.
- And it gave reasonable answers
and looked real and so on.
So to me, it's a, he
wasn't sufficiently trying
to stress the system I think
and exposing the truth of it
as it is today.
But I think this will be
increasingly harder over time.
So yeah, I think more and more
people will basically become,
yeah, I think there will be
more people like that over time
as this gets better.
- Like form an emotional
connection to an AI?
- Yeah.
Perfectly plausible in my mind.
I think these AIs are actually quite good
at human connection, human emotion.
A ton of text on the
internet is about humans,
and connection, and love, and so on.
So I think they have a very
good understanding in some sense
of how people speak to
each other about this.
And they're very capable of creating
a lot of that kind of text.
There's a lot of like sci-fi
from fifties and sixties
that imagined AIs in a very different way.
They are calculating,
cold, Vulkan-like machines.
That's not what we're getting today.
We're getting pretty emotional AIs
that actually are very
competent and capable
of generating plausible-sounding text
with respect to all these topics.
- See I'm really hopeful about AI systems
that are companions that help you grow,
develop as a human being,
help you maximize long-term happiness.
But I'm also very worried about AI systems
that figure out from the internet
that humans get attracted to drama.
And so these would just
be like shit-talking AIs
that just constantly, did you hear?
They'll do gossip,
they'll try to plant seeds
of suspicion to other humans
that you love and trust.
And just kind of mess with people
'cause that's going to
get a lot of attention.
So drama, maximize drama.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- On the path to maximizing engagement
and us humans will feed into that machine.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- And it'll be a giant drama shit storm-
So I'm worried about that.
So as the objective function
really defines the way
that human civilization
progresses with AIs in it.
- Yeah.
I think right now, at least today,
it's not correct to really think of them
as goal-seeking agents
that want to do something.
They have no long-term memory or anything,
a good approximation of it
is you get a thousand words
and you're trying to predict
a thousand of them first
and then you continue feeding it in
and you are free to prompt
it in whatever way you want.
So in text.
So you say okay you are a
psychologist and you are very good
and you love humans and
here's the conversation
between you and another human,
human column something, you something,
and then it just continues the pattern
and suddenly you're having a conversation
with a fake psychologist
who's trying to help you.
And so it's still kind
of a the realm of a tool,
people can prompt it in arbitrary ways
and it can create really incredible text
but it doesn't have long-term goals
over long periods of time.
So it doesn't look that way right now.
- Yeah.
But you can do short-term goals
that have long-term effects.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- So if my prompting short-term goal
is to get Andrej Karpathy to respond to me
on Twitter when I, I think
AI might, that's the goal,
but it might figure out
that talking shit to you,
it would be the best
in a highly sophisticated interesting way.
- [Andrej] Right.
- And then you build up a
relationship when you respond once
and then over time, it gets
to not be sophisticated
and just talk shit, and okay,
maybe you won't get to Andrej
but it might get to another celebrity,
it might get into other big accounts.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- So with just that simple
goal, get them to respond.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Maximize the probability
of actual response.
- Yeah.
I mean you could prompt a
powerful model like this
with its opinion about how to do
any possible thing you're interested in.
- [Lex] Yes.
- And they're kind of on
track to become these oracles,
I could think of it that way.
They are oracles currently it's just text
but they will have calculators,
they will have access to Google search,
they will have all kinds
of gadgets and gizmos.
They will be able to operate the internet
and find different information and yeah,
in some sense that's kinda like
currently what it looks like
in terms of the development.
- Do you think it'll be
an improvement eventually
over what Google is for
access to human knowledge?
It'll be a more effective search engine
to access human knowledge?
- I think there's definite scope
in building a better search engine today.
And I think Google,
they have all the tools,
all the people, they have
everything they need.
They have all the possible pieces,
they have people training
transformers at scale,
they have all the data.
It's just not obvious if they
are capable as an organization
to innovate on their
search engine right now
and if they don't someone else will.
There's absolute scope for
building a significantly better
search engine built on these tools.
- It's so interesting a large
company where the search,
there's already an
infrastructure, it works,
ads brings out a lot of money.
So where structurally inside a company
is their motivation to pivot.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- To say we're going to
build a new search engine.
- [Andrej] Yep.
- That's really hard.
- So it's usually going to
come from a startup, right?
- Yeah or some other more
competent organization.
So I don't know.
So currently for example, maybe
Bing has another shot at it,
as an example.
- [Lex] There you go, Microsoft Edge
as we're talking offline.
- It's really interesting
because search engines
used to be about okay here's some query,
here's web pages that look
like the stuff that you have.
But you could just directly go to answer
and then have supporting evidence.
And these models, basically,
they've read all the texts
and they've read all the web pages.
And so sometimes when you
see yourself going over
to search results and getting
a sense of the average answer
to whatever you're interested in,
that just directly comes out,
you don't have to do that work.
So they're kind of like-
Yeah, I think they have
a way to of distilling
all that knowledge into some
level of insight, basically.
- Do you think of prompting
as a teaching and learning,
like this whole process?
Like another layer?
'Cause maybe that's what humans are,
you already have that background model
and then the world is prompting you.
- Yeah, exactly.
I think the way we are
programming these computers now,
like GPTs, is converging
to how you program humans.
I mean, how do I program
humans via prompt?
I go to people and I
prompt them to do things,
I prompt them for information.
And so natural language prompt
is how we program humans
and we're starting to
program computers directly
in that interface.
It's pretty remarkable honestly.
- So you've spoken a lot about
the idea of Software 2.0.
All good ideas become cliches so quickly,
like the terms, it's kind of hilarious.
It's like, I think Eminem once said that
if he gets annoyed by a song
he's written very quickly,
that means it's gonna be a big
hit 'cause it's too catchy.
But can you describe this idea
and how you're thinking about
it has evolved over the months
and years since you coined it?
- Yeah.
Yeah.
So I had a blog post on Software 2.0,
I think several years ago now.
And the reason I wrote that post is
because I saw something
remarkable happening
in software development
and how a lot of code
was being transitioned to be written
not in C++ and so on, but it's written
in the weights of a neural net.
Basically just saying that neural nets
are taking over software,
the realm of software
and taking more and more and more tasks.
And at the time, I think not
many people understood this
deeply enough that this is a big deal.
This is a big transition.
Neural networks were seen as one
of multiple classification
algorithms you might use
for your dataset problem on Kaggle.
This is not that,
this is a change in how
we program computers.
And I saw neural nets as
this is going to take over,
the way we program computers
is going to change,
it's not going to be people
writing software in C++
or something like that
and directly programming the software.
It's going to be accumulating
training sets and data sets
and crafting these objectives
by which we train these neural nets.
And at some point, there's going
to be a compilation process
from the dataset and the objective
and the architecture
specification into the binary,
which is really just
the neural net weights
and the forward pass of the neural net
and then you can deploy that binary.
And so I was talking about that transition
and that's what the post is about.
And I saw this play
out in a lot of fields,
autopilot being one of them,
but also just a simple
image classification.
People thought originally,
in the eighties and so on,
that they would write the
algorithm for detecting a dog
in an image and they had all these ideas
about how the brain does it
and first, we detected corners
and then we detect lines
and then we stitched them up
and they were really going at it.
They were thinking about
how they're gonna write the algorithm
and this is not the way you build it.
And there was a smooth
transition where, okay,
first we thought we were
gonna build everything,
then we were building the features,
so HOG features and things like that
that detect these little
statistical patterns
from image patches.
And then there was a little
bit of learning on top of it,
a support vector machine
or binary classifier
for cat versus dog and images
on top of the features.
So we wrote the features but
we trained the last layer,
as the classifier.
And then people are like,
actually, let's not
even design the features
because we can't, honestly,
we're not very good at it.
So let's also learn the features.
And then you end up with
basically a compilation neural net
where you're learning most of it.
You're just specifying the architecture.
And the architecture has
tons of filled-in blanks,
which is all the knobs and
you let the optimization
write most of it.
And so this transition is happening
across the industry everywhere.
And suddenly we end up with a ton of code
that is written in neural net weights.
And I was just pointing
out that the analogy
is actually pretty strong
and we have a lot of
developer environments
for Software 1.0.
We have IDEs, how you work with code,
how you debug code, how do you run code,
how do you maintain code?
We have GitHub.
So I was trying to make those
analogies in the new realm,
what is the GitHub of Software 2.0?
Turns out it's something
that looks like Hugging Face right now?
And so I think some
people took it seriously
and built cool companies and many people
originally attacked the post.
It actually was not well
received when I wrote it
and I think maybe it has
something to do with the title,
but the post was not well
received and I think more people
have been coming around to it over time.
- Yeah.
So you were the Director of AI at Tesla
where I think this idea was
really implemented at scale,
which is how you have engineering
teams doing Software 2.0.
So can you linger on that idea of,
I think we're in the really early stages
of everything you just said,
which is like GitHub, IDEs,
how do we build
engineering teams that work
in Software 2.0 systems
and the data collection
and the data annotation,
which is all part of that Software 2.0.
What do you think is the task
of programming Software 2.0?
Is it debugging in the
space of hyper-parameters
or is it also debugging the space of data?
- Yeah, the way by which
you program the computer
and influence its algorithm
is not by writing the commands yourself.
You're changing mostly the data set.
You're changing the loss functions
of what the neural net is trying to do,
how it's trying to predict things.
But basically the data sets
and the architectures of the neural net.
And so in the case of the autopilot,
a lot of the data sets have
to do with, for example,
detection of objects
and lane line markings
and traffic lights and so on.
So you accumulate massive data sets of,
here's an example,
here's the desired label
and then here's roughly what
the algorithm should look like.
And that's a compilation neural net.
So the specification of the
architecture is like a hint
as to what the algorithm
should roughly look like.
And then the fill in the
blanks process of optimization
is the training process.
And then you take your
neural net that was trained,
it gives all the right
answers on your data set
and you deploy it.
- So in that case, perhaps at
all machine learning cases,
there's a lot of tasks.
So is coming up formulating a task
for a multi-headed neural network,
is formulating a task
part of the programming?
- [Andrej] Yeah, pretty much so.
- How you break down a
problem into a set of tasks.
- Yeah.
On a high-level, I would say
if you look at the software
running in the autopilot,
I give a number of talks on this topic.
I would say originally
a lot of it was written
in Software 1.0, imagine
lots of C++, right?
And then gradually, there was
a tiny neural net that was,
for example, predicting
given a single image,
is there a traffic light or not?
Or is there a lane line marking or not?
And this neural net
didn't have too much to do
in the scope of the software,
it was making tiny predictions
on an individual little image
and then the rest of the
system stitched it up.
So okay, we don't have
just a single camera,
we have eight cameras,
we actually have eight cameras over time.
And so what do you do
with these predictions?
How do you put them together?
How do you do the fusion
of all that information
and how do you act on it?
All of that was written by humans in C++.
And then we decided, okay,
we don't actually want
to do all of that fusion in the C++ code
because we're actually not good enough
to write that algorithm.
We want the neural nets
to write the algorithm
and we want to port all of that
software into the 2.0 stack.
And so then we actually had neural nets
that now take all the eight
camera images simultaneously
and make predictions for all of that.
So, and actually, they
don't make predictions
in the space of images.
They now make predictions directly in 3D
and, actually, in three
dimensions around the car.
And now, actually, we don't
manually fuse the predictions
in 3D over time we don't trust ourselves
to write that tracker.
So actually, we give the neural net
the information over time.
So it takes these videos now
and makes those predictions.
And so you're just like
putting more and more power
into the neural net processing
and at the end of it,
the eventual goal is to
have most of the software
potentially be in the 2.0 end
because it works significantly better.
Humans are just not very good
at writing software, basically.
- So the prediction is
happening in this 4D land.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Was three-dimensional world over time.
- How do you do annotation in that world?
So data annotation, whether
it's self-supervised
or manual by humans is a big part
of this Software 2.0 world.
- I would say by far in the industry,
if you're talking about the industry
and what is the technology
of what we have available?
Everything is supervised learning.
So you need data sets
of input, desired output
and you need lots of it.
And there are three properties
of it that you need.
You need it to be very large,
you need it to be accurate, no mistakes
and you need it to be diverse.
You don't want to just have a lot
of correct examples of one thing.
You need to really cover the space
of possibility as much as you can.
And the more you can cover
the space of possible inputs,
the better the algorithm
will work at the end.
Now once you have really good data sets
that you're collecting,
curating and cleaning,
you can train your neural
net on top of that.
So a lot of the work goes
into cleaning those data sets.
Now, as you pointed out,
the question is how do
you achieve a ton of-
If you want to basically predict in 3D,
you need data in 3D to back that up.
So in this video, we have eight videos
coming from all the cameras of the system
and this is what they
saw and this is the truth
of what actually was
around, there was this car
and there was this car, this car,
these are the lane line markings,
this is the geometry of the road.
There's a traffic light in this
three-dimensional position,
you need the ground truth.
And so the big question that
team was solving, of course,
is how do you arrive at that ground truth?
Because once you have a million of it
and it's large, clean and diverse,
then training a neural net
on it works extremely well
and you can ship that into the car.
And so there's many mechanisms
by which we collected that training data.
You can always go for human annotation,
you can go for simulation
as a source of ground truth,
you can also go for what
we call the offline tracker
that we've spoken about
at the AI Day and so on,
which is basically an automatic
reconstruction process
for taking those videos and recovering
the three-dimensional reality
of what was around that car.
So basically, think of
doing a three-dimensional
reconstruction as an offline thing
and then understanding that okay,
there's 10 seconds of
video, this is what we saw
and therefore here's all the
lane lines, cars and so on.
And then once you have that annotation,
you can train neural nets to imitate it.
- And how difficult is
the 3D reconstruction?
- [Andrej] It's difficult
but it can be done.
- So there's overlap between the cameras
and you do the reconstruction
and perhaps if there's any inaccuracy
so that's caught in the annotation step.
- Yes.
The nice thing about the annotation
is that it is fully offline.
You have infinite time, you
have a chunk of one minute
and you're trying to just offline
in a super-computer somewhere.
Figure out where were all the
positions of all the cars,
of all the people, and you
have your full one minute
of video from all the angles
and you can run all the
neural nets you want
and they can be very
efficient, massive neural nets,
they can be neural net that
can't even run in the car
later at test time.
So they can be even more
powerful neural nets
than what you can eventually deploy.
So you can do anything you want,
three-dimensional
reconstruction, neural nets,
anything you want just
to recover that truth
and then you supervise that truth.
- What have you learned?
You said no mistakes about
humans doing annotation
'cause there's like a range
of things they're good at
in terms of clicking stuff on screen.
How interesting is that to
you of a problem of designing
an annotator where humans
are accurate, enjoy it,
what are they even the
metrics, are efficient,
are productive, all that kind of stuff?
- Yeah, so I grew the
annotation team at Tesla
from, basically, zero to a
thousand while I was there.
That was really interesting.
My background is a PhD student researcher.
So growing that kind of
organization was pretty crazy.
But yeah, I think it's
extremely interesting
and part of the design process very much
behind the autopilot as
to where you use humans.
Humans are very good at
certain kinds of annotations.
They're very good, for example,
at two-dimensional annotations of images.
They're not good at
annotating cars over time
in three-dimensional space.
Very, very hard.
And so that's why we're very
careful to design the tasks
that are easy to do for humans
versus things that should be
left to the offline tracker.
Maybe the computer will
do all the triangulation
and 3D construction but the human will say
exactly these pixels of the image are car.
Exactly these pixels are human.
And so co-designing the
data annotation pipeline
was very much bread and
butter what I was doing daily.
- Do you think there's
still a lot of open problems
in that space?
Just in general annotation
where the stuff the machines
are good at, machines do
and the humans do what they're good at
and there's maybe some iterative process?
- Right.
I think to a very large extent,
we went through a number of iterations
and we learned a ton about
how to create these data sets.
I'm not seeing big open problems.
Originally, when I joined
I was really not sure
how this would turn out.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- But by the time I left
I was much more secure
and actually, we understand the philosophy
of how to create these data sets
and I was pretty comfortable
with where that was at the time.
- So what are strengths
and limitations of cameras
for the driving task in your understanding
when you formulate the
driving task as a vision task
with eight cameras, you've
seen that the entire,
most of the history of
the computer vision field
when it has to do with neural networks.
Just if you step back,
what are the strengths
and limitations of pixels,
of using pixels to drive?
- Yeah, pixels I think
are a beautiful sensory,
beautiful sensor I would say.
The thing is like cameras
are very, very cheap
and they provide a ton of
information, ton of bits.
So it's a extremely cheap
sensor for a ton of bits.
And each one of these bits is a constraint
on the state of the world.
And so you get lots of
megapixel images, very cheap
and it just gives you
all these constraints
for understanding what's
actually out there in the world.
So vision is probably the
highest bandwidth sensor.
It's a very high bandwidth sensor.
- I love that pixels is a
constraint on the world.
It's this highly complex,
high bandwidth constraint
on the stage of the world.
That's fascinating.
- It's not just that, but
again this real importance
of it's the sensor that humans use,
therefore everything is
designed for that sensor.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- The text, the writing,
the flashing signs,
everything is designed for vision and so,
and you just find it everywhere.
And so that's why that is the
interface you want to be in
talking again about these
universal interfaces
and that's where we
actually want to measure
the world as well and then
develop software for that sensor.
- But there's other constraints
on the state of the world
that humans use to understand the world.
I mean vision ultimately is the main one.
But we're referencing our
understanding of human behavior
and some common-sense physics
that could be inferred
from vision, from a
perception perspective.
But it feels like we're
using some kind of reasoning
to predict the world.
- [Andrej] Yeah, hundred percent.
- Not just the pixels.
- I mean you have a powerful prior service
for how the world evolves
over time, et cetera.
So it's not just about the likelihood term
coming up from the data itself telling you
about what you are observing,
but also the prior term of
what are the likely things to see
and how do they likely move and so on.
- And the question is how complex
is the range of possibilities
that might happen
in the driving task.
- [Andrej] Right.
- Is that to you still an open problem
of how difficult is driving,
philosophically speaking?
Of al the time you worked on driving,
do you understand how hard driving is?
- Yeah, driving is really hard
because it has to do with the predictions
of all these other agents
and the theory of mind
and what they're gonna do.
And are they looking at you?
Where are they looking?
What are they thinking?
- [Lex] Yeah.
- There's a lot that goes
there at the full tail-off,
the expansion of the nines
that we have to be
comfortable with eventually
the final problems are of that form.
I don't think those are the
problems that are very common.
I think eventually they're important
but it's really in the tail end.
- In the tail end, the rare edge cases.
- [Andrej] Yes.
- From the vision perspective,
what are the toughest parts
of the vision problem of driving?
- Well, basically, the
sensor is extremely powerful
but you still need to
process that information.
And so going from brightnesses
of these pixel values
to, hey, here are the
three-dimensional world,
is extremely hard and that's
what the neural networks
are fundamentally doing.
And so the difficulty really is in just
doing an extremely good job of engineering
the entire pipeline,
the entire data engine,
having the capacity to
train these neural nets,
having the ability to evaluate
the system and iterate on it.
So I would say just doing
this in production at scale
is the hard part, it's
an execution problem.
- So the data engine but also
the deployment of the system
such that has low latency performance.
So it has to do all these steps.
- Yeah.
For the neural nets
specifically just making sure
everything fits into the chip on the car.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And you have a finite budget of flops
that you can perform and memory bandwidth
and other constraints and you
have to make sure it flies
and you can squeeze in as much computer
as you can into the tiny.
- What have you learned from that process?
Because maybe that's one
of the bigger, new things,
coming from a research background,
where there's a system that has to run
under heavily constrained resources.
Has to run really fast.
What insights have you learned from that?
- Yeah, I'm not sure if
there's too many insights,
you're trying to create a neural net
that will fit in what you have available
and you're always trying to optimize it.
And we talked a lot about it on the AI Day
and, basically, the triple backflips
that the team is doing
to make sure it all fits
and utilizes the engine.
So I think it's extremely good engineering
and then there's all kinds of
little insights peppered in
on how to do it properly.
- Let's actually zoom out
'cause I don't think we
talked about the data engine,
the entirety of the layouts of this idea
that I think is just beautiful
with humans in the loop.
Can you describe the data engine?
- Yeah, the data engine is what I call
the almost biological feeling process
by which you perfect the training sets
for these neural networks.
So because most of the
programming now is in the level
of these data sets and
make sure they're large,
diverse and clean, basically
you have a data set
that you think is good,
you train your neural net,
you deploy it, and then you
observe how well it's performing
and you're trying to
always increase the quality
of your data set.
So you're trying to catch scenarios,
basically, that are, basically, rare.
And it is in these scenarios
that neural nets will
typically struggle in
because they weren't told
what to do in those rare cases
in the data set.
But now you can close the loop
because if you can now
collect all those at scale,
you can then feed them back
into the reconstruction process
I described and reconstruct
the truth in those cases
and add it to the dataset.
And so the whole thing
ends up being a staircase
of improvement of
perfecting your training set
and you have to go through deployments
so that you can mine the parts
that are not yet represented
well on the dataset.
So your dataset is basically imperfect.
It needs to be diverse, it
has pockets that are missing
and you need to pat out the pockets.
You can sort of think of
it that way in the data.
- What role do humans play in this?
So what's this biological
system like a human body
made up of cells?
What role?
How do you optimize the human system?
The multiple engineers collaborating,
figuring out what to focus
on, what to contribute,
which task to optimize
in this neural network.
Who's in charge of figuring
out which task needs more data?
Can you speak to the
hyperparameters, the human system?
- It really just comes down
to extremely good execution
from an engineering team that
knows what they're doing.
They understand intuitively
the philosophical insights
underlying the data engine and the process
by which the system
improves and how to, again,
delegate the strategy
of the data collection
and how that works.
And then just making sure it's
all extremely well executed.
And that's where most of the work,
it's not even the
philosophizing or the research
or the ideas of it.
It's just extremely good
execution is so hard
when you're dealing
with data at that scale.
- So your role in the
data engine executing well
and it is difficult and
extremely important.
Is there a priority of a
vision board of saying like,
we really need to get
better at stoplights?
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- The prioritization of tasks?
- [Andrej] Yes.
- Is that essentially, and
that comes from the data?
- That comes to, a very large extent
to what we are trying to
achieve in the product roadmap.
The release we're trying
to get out and the feedback
from the QA team where the
system is struggling or not,
the things we're trying to improve.
- And the QA team gives some
signal, some information
in aggregate about the
performance of the system
in various conditions.
- That's right.
And then of course all of us drive it
and we can also see it.
It's really nice to work with a system
that you can also experience yourself.
It drives you home.
- Is there some insight you can draw
from your individual experience
that you just can't quite get
from an aggregate
statistical analysis of data?
- I would say so, yeah.
- [Lex] It's so weird, right?
- Yes.
- It's not scientific in a sense
'cause you're just one anecdotal sample.
- Yeah, I think there's a ton
of, it's a source of truth.
It's your interaction with the system.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And you can see it,
you can play with it,
you can perturb it, you
can get a sense of it,
you have an intuition for it.
I think numbers and plots
and graphs are much harder.
It hides a lot of-
- It's like if you train a language model,
it's a really powerful way is
by you interacting with it.
- [Andrej] Yeah, a hundred percent.
- Start try to build up an intuition.
- Yeah, I think Elon also,
he always wanted to
drive the system himself.
He drives a lot and I don't
wanna say almost daily.
So he also sees this as a source of truth,
you driving the system and
it performing and yeah.
- So what do you think?
Tough questions here.
So, Tesla, last year removed
radar from the sensor suite
and now just announce
that it's gonna remove
all ultrasonic sensors
relying solely on vision,
so camera only, does that
make the perception problem
harder or easier?
- I would almost reframe
the question in some way.
So the thing is basically,
you would think that additional sensors.
- Wait, wait, wait, can I just interrupt?
- [Andrej] Go ahead.
- I wonder if a language
model will ever do that
if you prompt it.
Let me reframe your question.
That would be epic.
That's the wrong prompt.
Sorry.
- Yeah, so it's a little
bit of a wrong question
because, basically, you would
think that these sensors
are an asset to you.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- But if you fully
consider the entire product
in its entirety, these sensors
are actually potentially a liability
because these sensors aren't free.
They don't just appear on your car.
Suddenly you have an entire supply chain,
you have people procuring it,
there can be problems with
them, they may need replacement.
They are part of the
manufacturing process.
They can hold back the
line in the production.
You need to source them,
you need to maintain them,
you have to have teams that
ride the firmware, all of it.
And then you also have
to incorporate them,
infuse them into the system in some way.
And so it actually bloats a lot of it.
And I think Elon is really
good at simplify, simplify,
best part is no part.
And he always tries to throw away things
that are not essential because
he understands the entropy
in organizations and an approach.
And I think in this case the cost is high
and you're not potentially seeing it
if you're just a computer vision engineer
and I'm just trying to improve my network
and is it more useful or less useful?
How useful is it?
And the thing is, if once
you consider the full cost
of a sensor, it actually
is potentially a liability
and you need to be really sure
that it's giving you
extremely useful information.
In this case, we looked at
using it or not using it
and the delta was not massive.
And so it's not useful.
- Is it also bloat in the data engine,
like having more sensors?
- Hundred percent.
- Is it a distraction?
- And these sensors, they
can change over time.
For example, you can have
one type of say radar,
you can have other type of radar.
They change over time.
Now suddenly you need to worry about it.
Now suddenly you have a
column in your sequel light
telling you, oh, what sensor type was it?
And they all have different distributions
and then they contribute noise
and entropy into everything
and they bloat stuff.
And also organizationally,
it's been really fascinating to me
that it can be very distracting.
If all you wanna get to work is vision,
all the resources are on it
and you're building out a data engine
and you're actually
making forward progress
because that is the sensor
with the most bandwidth,
the most constraints on the world.
And you're investing fully into that.
And you can make that extremely good.
You have only a finite amount
of sort of spend of focus
across different facets of the system.
- And this reminds me of Rich
Sutton, "The Bitter Lesson"
that just seems like
simplifying the system.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- In the long run.
And of course, you don't
know what the long run is
and it seems to be always
the right solution.
- Yeah.
Yes.
- In that case, it was for RL
but it seems to apply generally
across all systems that do computation.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- So what do you think about
the LiDAR as a crutch debate?
The battle between
point clouds and pixels?
- Yeah, I think this debate
is always slightly confusing
to me because it seems
like the actual debate
should be about do you
have the fleet or not.
That's the really important thing
about whether you can achieve
a really good functioning
of an AI system at this scale.
- [Lex] So data collection systems.
- Yeah.
Do you have a fleet or not is
significantly more important
whether you have LiDAR or not.
It's just another sensor.
And yeah, I think similar
to the radar discussion,
basically, yeah, I don't think it,
it basically doesn't
offer extra information.
It's extremely costly.
It has all kinds of problems.
You have to worry about it,
you have to calibrate it, et cetera.
It creates bloat and entropy.
You have to be really sure
that you need this sensor.
In this case, I basically
don't think you need it.
And I think honestly, I will
make a stronger statement.
I think some of the other
companies who are using it
are probably going to drop it.
- Yeah.
So you have to consider
the sensor in the full,
in considering can you build a big fleet
that collects a lot of data
and can you integrate that
sensor with that data,
and that sensor into a data engine
that's able to quickly find
different parts of the data
that then continuously improves
whatever the model that you're using.
- Yeah.
Another way to look at it
is like, vision is necessary
in a sense that the world is designed
for human visual consumption.
So you need vision, it's necessary.
And then also it is sufficient
because it has all the information
that you need for driving.
And humans obviously use vision to drive.
So it's both necessary and sufficient.
So you want to focus resources
and you have to be really sure
if you're going to bring in other sensors.
You could add sensors to infinity,
at some point you need to draw the line.
And I think in this case,
you have to really consider
the full cost of any one
sensor that you're adopting,
and do you really need it?
And I think the answer,
in this case, is no.
- So what do you think about the idea
that the other companies are
forming high-resolution maps
and constraining heavily
the geographic regions
in which they operate?
Is that approach, in your view,
not going to scale over time
to the entirety of the United States?
- [Andrej] Yeah.
I think-
- It'll take too long-
- As you've mentioned like they
pre-map all the environments
and they need to refresh the map
and they have a perfect
centimeter-level-accuracy map
of everywhere they're gonna drive.
It's crazy.
How are you going to, when
we're talking about autonomy
actually changing the
world, we're talking about
the deployment on the global scale
of autonomous systems for transportation.
And if you need to maintain
a centimeter-accurate map
for earth or for many cities
and keep them updated,
it's a huge dependency
that you're taking on,
a huge dependency.
It's a massive, massive dependency
and now you need to ask yourself,
do you really need it?
And humans don't need it, right?
So it's very useful to have
a low-level map of like,
okay, the connectivity of your road,
you know that there's a fork coming up.
When you drive in an environment,
you have that high-level understanding.
It's like a small Google map
and Tesla uses Google map,
similar resolution
information in its system,
but it will not pre-map environments
to centimeter-level accuracy.
It's a crutch, it's a distraction,
it causes entropy, and
it diffuses the team,
it dilutes the team
and you're not focusing
on what's actually necessary,
which is a computer vision problem.
- What did you learn
about machine learning,
about engineering, about
life, about yourself
as one human being from
working with Elon Musk?
- I think the most I've learned is about
how to run organizations efficiently
and how to create efficient organizations
and how to fight entropy
in an organization.
- So human engineering in
the fight against entropy.
- Yeah, I think Elon is
a very efficient warrior
in the fight against
entropy in organizations.
- What does entropy in an
organization look like exactly?
- It's process.
It's process and it's-
- Inefficiencies in the form meetings
and that kind of stuff?
- Yeah.
Meetings, he hates meetings,
he keeps telling people
to skip meetings if they're not useful.
He basically runs the
world's biggest startups,
I would say, Tesla, SpaceX are
the world's biggest startups.
Tesla actually is multiple startups,
I think it's better to
look at it that way.
And so I think he's
extremely good at that.
And yeah, he is a very good intuition
for streamlining process.
He's making everything efficient.
Best part is no part, simplifying,
focusing, and just kind
of removing barriers,
moving very quickly, making big moves.
All this is very startupy
sort of seeming things
but at scale.
- So strong drive to simplify.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- From your perspective, I mean,
that also probably applies
to just designing systems
and machine learning, and otherwise.
- Yeah.
- [Lex] like simplify, simplify.
- Yes.
- What do you think is
the secret to maintaining
the startup culture in
a company that grows?
Is there, can you introspect that?
- I do think he needs someone
in a powerful position
with a big hammer like
Elon who's the cheerleader
for that idea, and ruthlessly pursues it.
If no one has a big enough hammer,
everything turns into committees,
democracy within the company, process,
talking to stakeholders, decision-making,
Just everything just crumbles.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- If you have a big person
who is also really smart
and has a big hammer, things move quickly.
- So you said your favorite
scene in "Interstellar"
is the intense docking scene
with the AI and Cooper talking,
saying, "Cooper, what are you doing?
Docking.
It's not possible.
No, it's necessary."
Such a good line, by the way,
just so many questions there.
Why an AI in that scene presumably
is supposed to be able to
compute a lot more than the human
is saying it's not
optimal, why are the human,
I mean that's a movie,
but shouldn't the AI know
much better than the human?
Anyway, what do you think is the value
of setting seemingly impossible goals?
So like our initial intuition,
which seems like something
that you have taken on
that Elon espouses that
where the initial intuition
of the community might
say this is very difficult
and then you take it on
anyway, with a crazy deadline.
You, just from a human
engineering perspective,
have you seen the value of that?
- I wouldn't say that setting
impossible goals exactly
is a good idea but I think
setting very ambitious goals
is a good idea.
I think there's a, what
I call sublinear scaling
of difficulty, which
means that 10x problems
are not 10x hard.
Usually, 10x harder problem
is like two or three x
harder to execute on.
Because if you wanna actually,
like if you wanna improve a system by 10%,
it costs some amount of work.
And if you wanna 10x improve the system,
it doesn't cost you know,
a 100x amount of the work.
And it's because you
fundamentally change the approach.
And if you start with that constraint,
then some approaches are obviously dumb
and not going to work and
it forces you to reevaluate.
And I think it's a very interesting way
of approaching problem-solving.
- But it requires a
weird kind of thinking.
It's just going back to your PhD days.
It's like how do you think which ideas
in the machine learning
community are solvable?
- [Andrej] Yes.
- It requires, what is that?
I mean there's the cliche
of first principles thinking
but it requires to basically ignore
what the community is saying.
'Cause doesn't a community,
doesn't a community in science
usually draw lines of what
is and isn't possible?
- [Andrej] Right.
- And it's very hard to break out of that
without going crazy.
- Yeah.
I mean I think a good example here
is the deep learning
revolution in some sense
because you could be in
computer vision at that time,
during the deep learning
revolution of 2012 and so on.
You could be improving a
computer vision stack by 10%
or it can just be saying
actually all this is useless
and how do I do 10x
better computer vision?
Well, it's not probably by
tuning a HOG feature detector,
I need a different approach.
I need something that is scalable.
Going back to Richard Suttons
and understanding the philosophy
of the Bitter Lesson and then being like
actually, I need a much
more scalable system,
like a neural network
that in principle works.
And then having some deep
believers that can actually
execute on that mission, make it work.
So that's the 10x solution.
- What do you think is the
timeline to solve the problem
of autonomous driving?
That's still in part an open question.
- Yeah, I think the tough
thing with timelines
of self-driving obviously, is that no one
has created self-driving.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- So it's not like, what
do you think is a timeline
to build this bridge?
Well, we've built a
million bridges before,
here's how long that takes.
No one has built autonomy,
it's not obvious.
Some parts turn out to be
much easier than others.
So it's really hard to forecast.
You do your best based
on trend lines and so on
and based on intuition.
But that's why fundamentally
it's just really hard
to forecast this.
No one has-
- So even still like being inside of it,
it's hard to-
- Yes.
Some things turn out to be much harder
and some things turned
out to be much easier.
- Do you try to avoid making forecasts?
'Cause Elon doesn't avoid them, right?
And heads of car companies in the past
have not avoided it either.
Ford and other places
have made predictions
that we're gonna solve level-four driving
by 2020, 2021, whatever.
And they all backtrack on that prediction.
As an AI person, do you
feel yourself privately
make predictions or do they get in the way
of your actual ability
to think about a thing?
- Yeah, I would say what's easy to say
is that this problem is tractable
and that's an easy prediction to make.
It's tractable-
- So it's solvable?
- It's going to work.
Yes.
It's just really hard.
Some things turned out to be harder
and somethings turn out to be easier.
But it definitely feels tractable
and it feels like, at
least the team at Tesla,
which is what I saw internally,
is definitely on track to that.
- How do you form a strong representation
that allows you to make a
prediction about tractability?
So you're the leader a lot of humans,
you have to say this is actually possible.
- Yeah.
- How do you build up that intuition?
It doesn't have to be even driving,
it could be other tasks.
- [Andrej] Right.
- It could be, what difficult
tasks did you work on
in your life?
I mean classification, achieving certain,
just an image at certain level
of superhuman-level performance.
- Yeah, expert intuition.
It's just intuition, it's belief.
- So just like thinking about
it long enough, like studying,
looking at sample data,
like you said, driving.
My intuition is really flawed on this.
I don't have a good
intuition about tractability.
It could be anything.
It could be solvable.
The driving task could be simplified
into something quite trivial.
Like the solution to the
problem would be quite trivial.
And at scale, more and
more cars driving perfectly
might make the problem much easier.
The more cars you have driving,
like people learn how to drive
correctly, not correctly,
but in a way that's more
optimal for heterogeneous system
of autonomous, and semi-autonomous,
and manually driven cars,
that could change stuff.
Then again, also I've spent
a ridiculous number of hours
just staring at pedestrians
crossing streets,
thinking about humans.
And it feels like the way
we use our eye contact,
it sends really strong signals
and there's certain quirks
and edge cases of behavior.
And of course, a lot of
the fatalities that happen
have to do with drunk driving,
both on the pedestrian
side and the driver's side.
So there's that problem
of driving at night
and all that kind of.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- So I wonder, it's like the
space of possible solution
into autonomous driving includes
so many human factor issues
that it's almost impossible to predict.
There could be super
clean, nice solutions.
- Yeah.
I would say definitely,
to use a game analogy,
there's some fog of war,
but you definitely also see
the frontier of improvement and
you can measure historically
how much you've made progress.
And I think for example,
at least what I've seen
in roughly five years at Tesla.
When I joined it barely
kept lane on the highway.
I think going up from Palo Alto to SF
was like three or four interventions.
Anytime the road would
do anything geometrically
or turn too much it would just not work.
And so going from that to
like a pretty competent system
in five years and seeing what
happens also under the hood
and what the scale which
the team is operating now
with respect to data, and
compute, and everything else
is just massive progress.
- So you're climbing a
mountain and it's fog
but you're making a lot of progress.
- It's Fog.
You're making progress and you see
what the next directions are
and you're looking at some
of the remaining challenges
and they're not perturbing you,
and they're not changing your philosophy,
and you're not contorting yourself.
You're like, actually,
these are the things
that we still need to do.
- Yeah, it's the fundamental components
of solving the problem seem to be there,
from the data engine, to the compute,
to the compute on the car, to
the compute for the training,
all that kind of stuff.
- [Andrej] Yes.
- Over the years you've been at Tesla,
you've done a lot of
amazing breakthrough ideas
and engineering all of
it from the data engine
to the human side, all of it.
Can you speak to why you
chose to leave Tesla?
- Basically, as I
described, I think over time
during those five years
I've kind of gotten myself
into a little bit of
a managerial position.
Most of my days were meetings,
and growing the organization,
and making decisions about,
high-level strategic
decisions about the team
and what it should be
working on, and so on.
And it's kind of like a
corporate executive role.
And I can do it.
I think I'm okay at it.
But it's not like
fundamentally what I enjoy.
And so I think when I joined,
there was no computer vision team
because Tesla was just
going from the transition
of using MobilEye, a third-party vendor,
for all of its computer vision
to having to build its
computer vision system.
So when I showed up, there were two people
training deep neural networks.
And they were training them at a computer
at their legs, like
down, there was a work.
- There was some kind of
basic classification task.
- Yeah.
And so I like grew that into what I think
is a fairly respectable
deep learning team,
a massive computer cluster,
a very good data annotation organization.
And I was very happy with where that was.
It became quite autonomous
and so I stepped away
and I'm very excited to do much
more technical things again.
Yeah.
And kind of like we focus on AGI.
- What was that soul searching like?
'Cause you took a little
time off, I think,
how many mushrooms did you take?
No, I'm just kidding.
I mean, what was going through your mind?
The human lifetime is finite.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- You did a few incredible things.
You're one of the best
teachers of AI in the world.
You're one of the best.
And I mean that in the best possible way.
You're one of the best
tinkerers in the AI world.
Meaning like understanding
the fundamentals
of how something works by
building it from scratch
and playing with the basic intuitions.
It's like Einstein, Fineman,
were all really good
at this kind of stuff.
Like small example of a
thing, to play with it,
to try to understand it.
So that, and obviously now with Tesla,
you helped build a team
of machine learning
engineers and a system that
actually accomplishes something
in the real-world.
So given all that, what was
the soul searching like?
- Well, it was hard because obviously,
I love the company a lot, and
I love Elon, I love Tesla,
so it was hard to leave.
I love the team, basically.
But yeah, I think I actually,
I really potentially
interested in revisiting it,
maybe coming back at some
point, working in Optimus,
working in AGI at Tesla.
I think Tesla's going
to do incredible things.
It's basically a massive
large-scale robotics
kind of company with a
ton of in-house talent
for doing real incredible things.
And I think human robots
are going to be amazing.
I think autonomous transportation
is going to be amazing.
All this is happening at Tesla.
So I think it's just a
really amazing organization.
So being part of it and helping it along
I think was very, basically,
I enjoyed that a lot.
Yeah, it was basically
difficult for those reasons
because I love the company.
But I'm happy to potentially at some point
come back for act two.
But I felt like at this
stage I built the team,
it felt autonomous and I became a manager
and I wanted to do a lot
more technical stuff.
I wanted to learn stuff.
I wanted to teach stuff.
And I just felt like it was a good time
for a change of pace a little bit.
- What do you think is
the best movie sequel
of all time speaking of part two?
'Cause most of 'em suck.
- Movie sequels?
- Movie sequels, yeah.
And you Tweet about movies.
So just a tiny tangent, what's
a favorite movie sequel?
"Godfather Part II"?
Are you a fan of "Godfather"?
'Cause you didn't even Tweet
or mention "The Godfather".
- Yeah, I don't love that movie.
I know it has a-
- We're gonna edit that out.
We're gonna edit out the
hate towards "The Godfather".
How dare you disrespect?
- I think I will make a strong statement.
I don't know why but I
basically don't like any movie
before 1995, something like that.
- Didn't you mention "Terminator 2".
- Okay.
Okay.
That's like a, "Terminator
2" was a little bit later.
1990...
- No, I think "Terminator
2" was in the eighties.
- And I like "Terminator" one as well,
So, okay.
So a few exceptions but by and large
for some reason, I don't like movies
before 1995 or something.
They feel very slow.
The camera is like zoomed out.
It's boring, it's kind of
naive, it's kind of weird.
- And also Terminator was
very much ahead of its time.
- Yes.
And "The Godfather", there's like no AGI.
- I mean but you have, "Good Will Hunting"
was one of the movies you mentioned
and that doesn't have any AGI either.
I guess it has mathematics.
- Yeah, I guess occasionally,
I do enjoy movies
that don't feature.
- Or like "Anchorman" that has no, that's.
- "Anchorman" is so good.
- I don't understand, speaking of AGI,
'cause I don't understand
why Will Ferrell is so funny.
It doesn't make sense.
It doesn't compute.
There's just something about him.
And he's a singular human.
'Cause, you don't get that
many comedies these days.
And I wonder if it has
to do about the culture
or the Machine of Hollywood
or does it have to do with
just we got lucky with
certain people in comedy
that came together, 'cause
he is a singular human.
- Yeah, yeah.
I love his movies.
- That was a ridiculous
tangent, I apologize.
But you mentioned humanoid robots.
So what do you think about
Optimus, about Tesla Bot?
Do you think we'll have
robots in the factory
and in the home in 10,
20, 30, 40, 50 years?
- Yeah.
I think it's a very hard project.
I think it's going to take a while,
but who else is going to
build human robots at scale?
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And I think it is a very
good form factor to go after
because like I mentioned
the world is designed
for humanoid form factor.
These things would be able
to operate our machines.
They would be able to sit down in chairs,
potentially even drive cars.
Basically, the world
is designed for humans,
that's the form factor
you want to invest into
and make work over time.
I think, there's another
school of thought which is,
okay, pick a problem and
design a robot to it.
But actually, designing a robot
and getting a whole data engine
and everything behind it to work
is actually an incredibly hard problem.
So it makes sense to go
after general interfaces
that, okay, they are not
perfect for any one given task,
but they actually have the
generality of just with a prompt,
with English, able to do something across.
And so I think it makes a lot of sense
to go after a general interface
in the physical world.
And I think it's a very difficult project.
It's going to take time, but
I've seen no other company
that can execute on that vision.
I think it's going to be amazing.
Basically, physical labor,
if you think transportation
is a large market, try physical labor.
It's insane.
- But it's not just physical labor, to me,
the thing that's also exciting
is the social robotics.
So the relationship we'll
have on different levels
with those robots.
- Yeah.
- That's why I was really
excited to see Optimus.
People have criticized
me for the excitement,
but I've worked with
a lot of research labs
that do humanoid-legged robots,
Boston Dynamics, Unitree.
There's a lot of companies
that do legged robots,
but that's the elegance of the movement
is a tiny, tiny part of the big picture.
So the two big exciting
things to me about Tesla
doing humanoid or any legged robots
is clearly integrating
into the data engine.
So the data engine aspect,
so the actual intelligence
for the perception and the
control and the planning
and all that kind of stuff.
Integrating into this huge,
the fleet that you mentioned.
Right.
And then speaking of
fleet, the second thing is
the mass manufacturers just knowing
culturally driving towards a simple robot
that's cheap to produce at scale.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- And doing that well, having
experience to do that well,
that changes everything.
That's why that's a very different culture
and style than Boston Dynamics.
Who by the way, those robots are just-
The way they move, it'll
be a very long time
before Tesla could achieve
the smoothness of movement.
But that's not what it's about.
It's about the entirety of the system.
Like we talked about the
data engine and the fleet.
- [Andrej] Right.
- And that's super exciting,
even the initial sort of models.
But that too was really surprising
that in a few months you
can get a pro a prototype.
- Yep.
And the reason that
happened very quickly is,
as you alluded to, there's
a ton of copy-paste
from what's happening in the autopilot.
A lot.
The amount of expertise that
came out of the woodworks
at Tesla for building the human
robot was incredible to see.
Basically, Elon said at
one point we're doing this
and then next day, basically,
all these CAD models
started to appear and people
talk about the supply chain
and manufacturing.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And people showed up with
Screwdrivers and everything
the other day and started to
like put together the body.
And I was like, whoa.
All these people exist at Tesla.
And fundamentally building a car
is actually not that different
from building a robot.
And that is true not just
for the hardware pieces.
And also let's not forget
hardware, not just for a demo,
but manufacturing of
that hardware at scale
is a whole different thing.
But for software as well,
basically, this robot
currently thinks it's a car.
- It's gonna have a midlife
crisis at some point.
- It thinks it's a car.
Some of the earlier demos,
actually, we were talking about
potentially doing them
outside in the parking lot
because that's where all
of the computer vision
was working out of the box.
- [Lex] That's Funny.
- Instead of inside.
But all the operating system,
everything just copy-pastes,
computer vision mostly copy-paste.
I mean you have to
retrain the neural nets,
but the approach and
everything and data engine
and offline trackers
and the way we go about
the occupancy tracker and so on.
Everything copy-paste,
you just need to retrain the neural nets.
And then the planning control, of course,
has to change quite a bit,
but there's a ton of copy-paste
from what's happening at Tesla.
And if you were to go
with goal of like, okay,
let's build a million human
robots and you're not Tesla,
that's a lot to ask, if you're at Tesla,
it's actually like, that's not that crazy.
- And then the follow-up question is then
how difficult, just like with driving,
how difficult is the manipulation task?
- [Andrej] Yep.
- Such that it can have
an impact at scale?
I think depending on the context,
the really nice thing
about robotics is that,
unless you do a manufacturer
and that kind of stuff,
is there is more room for error?
- [Andrej] Yep.
- Driving is so safety-critical
and also time critical,
a robot is allowed to move
slower, which is nice.
- Yes.
I think it's going to take a long time.
But the way you want to
structure the development
is you need to say, okay, it's
going to take a long time.
How can I set up the
product development roadmap
so that I'm making revenue along the way?
I'm not setting myself up
for a zero-one-loss function
where it doesn't work until it works.
You don't wanna be in that position.
You want to make it
useful almost immediately.
And then you want to slowly deploy it and-
- [Lex] At scale, hopefully.
- At scale and you want to
set up your data engine,
your improvement loops, the
telemetry, the evaluation,
the harness and everything.
And you want to improve the product
over time, incrementally.
And you're making revenue along the way.
That's extremely important
because otherwise, you cannot build
these large undertakings,
just don't make sense economically.
And also from the point of
view of the team working on it,
they need the dopamine along the way.
They're not just going to make a promise
about this being useful.
This is going to change the
world in 10 years when it works.
This is not where you want to be.
You want to be in a place
like I think autopilot today
where it's offering increased safety
and convenience of driving today.
People pay for it, people
like it, people purchase it.
And then you also have the greater mission
that you're working towards.
- And you see that.
So the dopamine for the team,
that was the source of happiness?
- Yes, hundred percent,
you're deploying this.
People like it, people
drive it, people pay for it,
they care about it.
There's all these YouTube
videos, your grandma drives it.
She gives you feedback.
People like it, people engage with it.
You engage with it.
Huge.
- Do people that drive
Teslas recognize you
and give you love?
Like, hey thanks for this
nice feature that it's doing.
- Yeah, I think the tricky thing is
some people really love you,
some people, unfortunately,
you're working on something that you think
is extremely valuable, useful, et cetera,
some people do hate you.
There's a lot of people
who hate me and the team
and the whole project.
And I think-
- Are they Tesla drivers?
- Many cases they're not, actually.
- Yeah.
That actually makes me sad about humans
or the current ways that humans interact.
I think that's actually fixable.
I think humans want to
be good to each other.
I think Twitter and social
media is part of the mechanism
that actually somehow makes
the negativity more viral
that it doesn't deserve,
disproportionately add a
viral boost of negativity.
But I wish people would
just get excited about,
so suppress some of the jealousy,
some of the ego and just
get excited for others.
And then there's a karma aspect to that.
You get excited for others,
they'll get excited for you.
Same thing in academia,
if you're not careful,
there is a dynamical system there.
If you think of in silos and get jealous
of somebody else being successful
that actually perhaps counterintuitively
leads the less productivity
of you as a community
and you individually.
I feel like if you keep
celebrating others,
that actually makes you more successful.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- And I think people haven't,
depending on the industry,
haven't quite learned that yet.
- Yeah.
Some people are also very
negative and very vocal.
So they're very prominently featured.
But actually, there's a ton of
people who are cheerleaders,
but they're silent cheerleaders.
And when you talk to
people just in the world,
they will all tell you
it's amazing, it's great.
Especially like people who understand
how difficult it is to
get this stuff working.
People who have built products
and makers and entrepreneurs,
making this work and changing
something is incredibly hard.
Those people are more
likely to cheerlead you.
- Well, one of the
things that makes me sad
is some folks in the robotics community
don't do the cheerleading and they should
'cause they know how difficult it is.
Well, they actually sometimes don't know
how difficult it is to
create a product at scale.
Right?
- [Andrej] Yep.
- They actually deploy in the real-world.
A lot of the development
of robots and AI systems
is done on very specific small benchmarks
and as opposed to real-world additions.
- Yes.
Yeah.
I think it's really
hard to work on robotics
in academic setting.
- Or AI systems that
apply in the real-world.
You've criticized, you
flourished, and loved
for time the ImageNet,
the famed ImageNet dataset
and have recently had
some words of criticism
that the academic research ML community
gives a little too much
love still to the ImageNet
or those kinds of benchmarks.
Can you speak to the strengths
and weaknesses of data sets
used in machine learning research?
- Actually, I don't know that
I recall the specific instance
where I was unhappy or
criticizing ImageNet.
I think ImageNet has
been extremely valuable.
It was basically a benchmark that allowed
the deep learning community to demonstrate
that deep neural nets actually work.
- [Lex] Yes.
- There's a massive value in that.
So I think ImageNet was
useful, but basically,
it's become a bit of an
EMNIST at this point.
So EMNIST is like little
28 by 28 grayscale digits.
That's kind of a joke data set
that everyone just crushes.
- There's still papers written
on EMNIST though, right?
Like strong papers?
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Like papers that focus
on like how do we learn
with a small amount of
data, that kinda stuff.
- Yeah.
Yeah, I could see that being helpful
but not in mainline
computer vision research
anymore, of course.
- I think the way I've
heard you just somewhere,
maybe I'm just imagining things,
but I think you said like
ImageNet was a huge contribution
to the community for a long time
and now it's time to
move past those kinds of-
- Well, ImageNet has been crushed.
I mean, the error rates are, yeah,
we're getting like 90% accuracy
in 1000 classification way prediction
and I've seen those images
and this is like really
high, that's really good.
If I remember correctly,
the top five error rate
is now like 1% or something.
- Given your experience with a
gigantic real-world data set,
would you like to see benchmarks move
into certain directions that
the research community uses?
- Unfortunately, I don't think academics
currently have the next ImageNet.
We've obviously, I think
we've crushed EMNIST.
We've basically crushed ImageNet
and there's no next-big benchmark
that the entire community
rallies behind and uses
for further development of these networks.
- Oh, yeah.
I wonder what it takes for a dataset
to captivate the imagination of everybody.
Like where they all get behind it.
That could also need a leader, right?
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Somebody with popularity.
I mean that, yeah, why
did ImageNet takeoff?
Is it just the accident of history?
- It was the right amount of difficult,
it was the right amount
of difficult and simple
and interesting enough
it was the right time
for that kind of a data set.
- Question from Reddit.
What are your thoughts on
the role that synthetic data
and game engines will play in the future
of neural net model development?
- I think as neural
nets converge to humans,
the value of simulation to neural nets
will be similar to value
of simulation to humans.
So people use simulation
because they can learn something
in that kind of a system
and without having
to actually experience it.
- But you're referring to the
simulation we do in our head?
Isn't that what thinking is?
- Oh no, sorry.
Simulation, I mean like
video games or other forms
of simulation for various professionals.
- Well, so let me push back on that
'cause maybe there's simulation
that we do in our heads,
like simulate if I do this,
what do I think will happen?
- [Andrej] Okay.
That's like internal simulation.
- Yeah, internal.
Isn't that what we're doing?
Assuming before we act.
- Oh, yeah.
But that's independent
from the use of simulation
in the sense of computer
games, or using simulation
for training set creation, or something.
- Is it independent or is
it just loosely correlated?
'Cause isn't that useful
to do counterfactual
or edge case simulation to what happens
if there's a nuclear war?
What happens if there's,
like those kinds of things?
- Yeah.
That's a different simulation
from Unreal Engine.
That's how I interpreted the question.
- Ah, so like simulation
of the average case?
What's Unreal Engine?
What do you mean by Unreal Engine?
So simulating a world.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- The physics of that world,
Why is that different?
'Cause you also can add
behavior to that world
and you could try all
kinds of stuff, right?
You could throw all kinds
of weird things into it.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Unreal Engine is not
just about simulating,
I mean I guess it is about simulating
the physics of the world,
it's also doing something with that.
- Yeah.
The graphics, the physics, and the agents
that you put into the
environment and stuff like that.
Yeah.
- I feel like you said that
it's not that important,
I guess, for the future of AI development.
Is that correct, to
interpret you that way?
- Well, I think, humans use simulators
and they find them useful and so computers
will use simulators and find them useful.
- Okay, so you're saying it's not,
I don't use simulators very often.
I play a video game every once in a while
but I don't think I derive any wisdom
about my own existence
from those video games.
It's a momentary escape from reality
versus a source of wisdom about reality.
So I think that's a very
polite way of saying
simulation is not that useful.
- Yeah.
Maybe not.
I don't see it as a fundamental,
really important part
of training neural nets currently.
But I think as neural nets
become more and more powerful,
I think you will need fewer examples
to train additional behaviors.
And simulation is, of
course, there's a domain gap
in a simulation that's not the real-world,
it's slightly something different.
But with a powerful enough neural net
you need the domain gap
can be bigger I think
because neural net will understand
that even though it's not the real-world,
it has all this high-level structure
that I'm supposed to learn from.
- So the neural net will actually, yeah,
it will be able to leverage
the synthetic data better?
- [Andrej] Yes.
- By closing the gap but understanding
in which ways this is not real data?
- [Andrej] Exactly.
- Reddit do better questions next time.
That was a question.
No, I'm just kidding.
All right, so is it
possible, do you think,
speaking of EMNIST to
construct neural nets
and training processes that
require very little data.
So we've been talking about huge data sets
like the internet for training.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- I mean one way to say
that is like you said,
the querying itself is another
level of training I guess
and that requires a little data.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- But do you see any
value in doing research
and going down the direction
of can we use very little data
to construct a knowledge base?
- A hundred percent.
I just think at some point
you need a massive data set
and then when you pre-train
your massive neural net
and get something that is
like a GPT or something,
then you're able to be very efficient
at training any arbitrary new task.
So a lot of these GPTs you can do tasks
like sentiment analysis,
or translation, or so on,
just by being prompted
with very few examples.
Here's the kind of thing I want you to do.
Like here's an input sentence,
here's the translation into German,
input sentence, translation to German,
input sentence, blank, and the neural net
will complete the translation to German
just by looking at the
example you've provided.
And so that's an example
of a very few shot learning
in the activations of the neural net,
instead of the weights of the neural net.
And so I think basically just like humans,
neural nets will become
very data efficient
at learning any other new task.
But at some point, you
need a massive data set
to pre-train your network.
- I do get that.
And probably, we humans
have something like that.
Do we have something like that?
Do we have a passive in the background,
background model constructing thing
that just runs all the time
in a self-supervised way?
We're not conscious of it?
- I think humans definitely,
I mean obviously,
we learn a lot during our lifespan,
but also we have a ton of hardware
that helps us, the initialization
coming from evolution.
And so I think that's also
a really big component.
A lot of people in the field,
I think they just talk about
the amounts of like seconds
that a person has lived,
pretending that this is a tabula rasa,
a zero initialization of a neural net.
And it's not.
You can look at a lot of
animals for example, zebras.
Zebras get born, and they
see, and they can run,
there's zero training
data in their lifespan.
They can just do that.
So somehow, I have no idea
how, evolution has found a way
to encode these algorithms
and these neural net initializations
that are extremely good into ATCGs.
And I have no idea how this works,
but apparently, it's possible
because here's proof by existence.
- There's something magical about
going from a single-cell
to an organism that is born
to the first few years of life.
I like the idea that the reason
we don't remember anything
about the first few years of our life
is that it's a really painful process.
Like it's a very difficult
challenging training process.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Like intellectually and maybe, yeah,
I mean I don't, why don't
we remember any of that?
That might be some crazy training going on
and maybe that's the
background model training
that is very painful.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- And so it's best for the
system once it's trained
not to remember how it was constructed.
- I think it's just like the
hardware for long-term memory
is just not fully developed.
- [Lex] Sure.
- I feel like the first
few years of infants,
it's not actually like
learning, it's brain maturing.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- We're born premature
and there's a theory
along those lines because
of the birth canal
and the swelling of the brain.
And so we're born premature
and then the first few years
we're just, the brain's maturing
and then there's some learning eventually.
It's my current view on it.
- What do you think, do
you think neural nets
can have long-term memory?
Like that approach is
something like humans?
Do you think there needs to
be another meta-architecture
on top of it to add something
like a knowledge base
that learns facts about the world
and all that kind of stuff?
- Yes, but I don't know to what extent
it will be explicitly constructed.
It might take on intuitive forms
where you are telling the GPT,
hey, you have a declarative memory bank
to which you can store
and retrieve data from
and whenever you
encounter some information
that you find useful just
save it to your memory bank.
And here's an example of
something you have retrieved
and here's how you say it and
here's how you load from it.
You just say, load whatever,
you teach it in text,
in English and then it might learn
to use a memory bank from that.
- Oh, so the neural
net is the architecture
for the background model, the base thing
and then everything else
is just on top of it.
- It's not just a text, right?
You're giving it gadgets and gizmos.
So you're teaching it some
kind of a special language
by which it can save arbitrary information
and retrieve it at a later time.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And you're telling
about these special tokens
and how to arrange them
to use these interfaces.
It's like, hey, you can use a calculator,
here's how you use it.
Just do five three plus four one equals
and when equals is there,
a calculator will actually
read out the answer
and you don't have to
calculate it yourself
and you just tell it in English,
this might actually work.
- Do you think in that
sense Gato is interesting,
the DeepMind system that
it's not just new language
but actually throws it
all in the same pile,
images, actions, all that kind of stuff.
That's basically what
we're moving towards.
- Yeah, I think so.
So Gato is very much a
kitchen sink of an approach
to reinforcement learning in
lots of different environments
with a single fixed transformer model.
Right?
I think it's a very early
result in that realm.
But I think, yeah, it's along the lines
of what I think things
will eventually look like.
- Right.
So this is the early days of a system
that eventually will look like this,
from a Rich Sutton perspective.
- Yeah.
I'm not a super huge fan of,
I think all these interfaces
that like look very different.
I would want everything to be
normalized into the same API.
So for example, screen
pixels, very same API
instead of having like
different world environments
that have very different
physics and joint configurations
and appearances and whatever.
And you're having some
kind of special tokens
for different games that you can plug.
I'd rather just normalize
everything to a single interface
so it looks the same to the
neural net if that makes sense.
- So it's all gonna be
pixel-based Pong in the end?
- [Andrej] I think so.
- Okay.
Let me ask you about
your own personal life.
A lot of people wanna know
you're one of the most productive
and brilliant people in the history of AI.
What is a productive day in the life
of Andrej Karpathy look like?
What time do you wake up?
'Cause imagine some kind of dance between
the average productive day
and a perfect productive day.
So the perfect productive day
is the thing we strive towards
and the average is kind
of what it converges to,
given all the mistakes and
human eventualities and so on.
- [Andrej] Yep.
- So what time did you wake up?
Are you a morning person?
- I'm not a morning person.
I'm a night owl, for sure.
- Is it stable or not?
- It's semi-stable like eight or nine
or something like that.
During my PhD, it was even
later, I used to go to sleep
usually at 3:00 AM, I think
the AM hours are precious
and a very interesting time to work
because everyone is asleep.
At 8:00 AM or 7:00 AM
the east coast is awake.
So there's already activity,
there's already some
text messages, whatever.
There's stuff happening.
You can go on some news website
and there's stuff
happening, it's distracting.
At 3:00 AM everything is totally quiet
and so you're not gonna be bothered
and you have solid chunks
of time to do work.
So I like those periods,
night owl by default.
And then I think productive time,
basically, what I like to
do is you need to build
some momentum on the problem
without too much distraction
and you need to load your
ram, your working memory
with that problem.
And then you need to be obsessed with it
when you're taking shower,
when you're falling asleep,
you need to be obsessed with the problem
and it's fully in your memory
and you're ready to wake up
and work on it right there.
- So is this in a scale
temporal scales of a single day
or a couple of days a week, a month?
- Yeah.
So I can't talk about one day, basically,
in isolation because it's a whole process.
When I wanna get
productive in the problem,
I feel like I need a span of a few days
where I can really get in on that problem
and I don't wanna be interrupted
and I'm going to just
be completely obsessed
with that problem.
And that's where I do most
of my good work, I would say.
- You've done a bunch of cool,
like little projects in a
very short amount of time,
very quickly, so that requires
you just focusing on it.
- Yeah, basically, I need
to load my working memory
with the problem and I
need to be productive
because there's always a huge fixed cost
to approaching any problem.
I was struggling with
this for example at Tesla
because I want to work on
small side project, but okay,
you first need to figure out,
oh, okay, I need to
associate into my cluster,
I need to bring up a VS Code
editor so I can work on this.
I ran into some stupid error
because of some reason.
You're not at a point
where you can be just
productive right away.
You are facing barriers.
And so it's about really
removing all of that barrier
and you're able to go into the problem
and you have the full problem
loaded in your memory.
- And somehow avoiding distractions
of all different forms.
- [Andrej] Yes.
- Like news stories, emails,
but also distractions
from other interesting projects
that you previously worked on
or currently working on and so on.
You just wanna really focus your mind.
- Yeah.
And I mean I can take some
time off for distractions
and in between, but I
think it can't be too much.
Most of your day is sort
of spent on that problem.
And then, I drink coffee,
I have my morning routine,
I look at some news, Twitter, Hacker News,
Wall Street Journal, et cetera.
It's great.
- So basically, you wake
up, you have some coffee,
are you trying to get to
work as quickly as possible?
Do you take in this diet of
what the hell's happening
in the world first?
- I do find it interesting
to know about the world.
I don't know that it's useful or good,
but it is part of my routine right now.
So I do read through a
bunch of news articles
and I wanna be informed
and I'm suspicious of it.
I'm suspicious of the practice,
but currently, that's where I am.
- Oh, you mean suspicious
about the positive effect?
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Of that practice on your
productivity and your well-being?
- My well-being, psychologically, yeah.
- And also on your ability to
deeply understand the world
because there's a bunch
of sources of information
you're not really focused
on deeply integrating it.
- Yeah, it's a little bit distracting.
Yeah.
- In terms of a perfectly productive day
for how long of a stretch
of time in one session
do you try to work and focus on a thing?
Is it a couple hours, is it
one hour, is it 30 minutes?
Is it 10 minutes?
- I can probably go a small few hours
and then I need some breaks in between
for food and stuff and yeah.
But I think, it's still really
hard to accumulate hours.
I was using a tracker that
told me exactly how much time
I spent coding any one day.
And even on a very productive day,
I still spent only six or eight hours.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And it's just because there's
so much padding, commute,
talking to people, food, et cetera.
There's a cost of life
just living and sustaining
and homeostasis and just
maintaining yourself
as a human is very high.
- And there seems to be a
desire within the human mind
to participate in society
that creates that padding.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- 'Cause the most productive
days I've ever had
is just completely from start to finish
is tuning out everything.
- [Andrej] Yep.
- And just sitting there
and then you could do more
than six in eight hours.
- Yep.
- Is there some wisdom about
what gives you strength
to do tough days of long focus?
- Yeah, just whenever I get
obsessed about a problem,
something just needs to work.
Something just needs to exist.
- It needs to exist.
So you're able to deal with
bugs and programming issues
and technical issues and design decisions
that turn out to be the wrong ones.
You're able to think through all of that
given that you want a thing to exist.
- Yeah, it needs to exist.
And then I think to me
also a big factor is,
are other humans are
going to appreciate it?
Are they going to like it?
That's a big part of my motivation.
If I'm helping humans and they seem happy,
they say nice things, they
Tweet about it or whatever,
that gives me pleasure because
I'm doing something useful.
- So you do see yourself
sharing it with the world?
With GitHub, with the blog
post or through videos?
- Yeah, I was thinking about it like,
suppose I did all these
things but did not share them.
I don't think I would have
the same amount of motivation
that I can build up.
- You enjoy the feeling of
other people gaining value
and happiness from the
stuff you've created.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- What about diet?
I saw you played with
intermittent fasting.
Do you fast?
Does that help?
- I play with everything.
- With the things you played,
what's been most beneficial
to your ability to
mentally focus on a thing
and just mental
productivity and happiness?
You still fast?
- Yeah.
I still fast but I do intermittent fasting
but really what it means
at the end of the day
is I skip breakfast.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- So I do 18/6 roughly by default
when I'm in my steady
state, if I'm traveling
or doing something else
I will break the rules.
But in my steady state, I do 18/6.
So I eat only from 12:00 to 6:00.
Not a hard rule and I break it
often, but that's my default.
And then, yeah, I've done a
bunch of random experiments
for the most part right now
where I've been for the last
year and a half I wanna say
is I'm plant-based or plant-forward.
I heard plant-forward, it sounds better.
- [Lex] What does that mean exactly?
- I don't actually know
what the difference is,
but it sounds better in my mind.
But it just means I prefer
plant-based food and-
- Raw or cooked.
- I prefer cooked and plant-based.
- So plant-based, forgive me,
I don't actually know
how wide the category
of plant entails.
- Well, plant-based just means
that you're not militant
about it and you can flex
and you just prefer to eat
plants and you're not making,
you're not trying to
influence other people.
And you come to someone's house party
and they serve you a steak
that they're really proud of,
you will eat it.
- Yes.
Right.
You're not judgmental.
That's beautiful.
I mean, I'm the flip side of that,
but I'm very sort of flexible.
Have you tried doing one meal a day?
- I have accidentally
but not consistently,
but I've accidentally had that.
I don't like it.
I think it makes me feel not good.
It's too much of a hit.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And so currently I have
about two meals a day,
12:00 and 6:00, probably.
- I do that nonstop.
I'm doing it now.
I do one meal a day.
- [Andrej] Okay.
- It's interesting.
It's an interesting feeling.
Have you ever fasted longer than a day?
- Yeah, I've done a bunch of water fasts.
'Cause I was curious what happens.
- [Lex] What happens,
anything interesting?
- Yeah, I would say so.
I mean, what's interesting
is that you're hungry
for two days and then
starting day three or so,
you're not hungry.
It's such a weird feeling
because you haven't eaten in a few days
and you're not hungry.
- Yeah, isn't that weird?
- [Andrej] It's really weird.
- One of the many weird
things about human biology.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- It figures something out,
it finds another source of
energy or something like that.
Or relaxes the system.
I don't know how it works.
- Yeah, the body is like,
"You're hungry, you're hungry."
And then it just gives up.
It's like, "Okay, I
guess we're fasting now."
There's nothing.
And then it's just focuses on
trying to make you not hungry
and not feel the damage of
that and trying to give you
some space to figure
out the food situation.
- So are you still to this
day most productive at night?
- I would say I am,
but it is really hard to
maintain my PhD schedule.
Especially, when I was say
working at Tesla and so on.
It's a non-starter.
But even now, people want
to meet for various events.
Society lives in a certain period of time.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And you have to work with that.
- It's hard to do a social thing
and then after that return and do work.
- Yeah.
It's just really hard.
- That's why I try,
when I do social thing,
I try not to do too much drinking
so I can return and continue doing work.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- But at Tesla is there
conversions, not Tesla,
but any company, is there a
convergence to always a schedule
or is that how humans behave
when they collaborate?
I need to learn about this?
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Do they try to keep
a consistent schedule
where you're all awake at the same time?
- I mean, I do try to create a routine
and I try to create a steady state
in which I'm comfortable in.
So I have a morning routine,
I have a day routine.
I try to keep things to a steady state
and things are predictable
and then your body just sticks to that.
And if you try to stress
that a little too much,
it will create, when you're traveling
and you're dealing with jet lag,
you're not able to really
ascend to where you need to go.
- Yeah.
Yeah.
That's weird too about us humans
with the habits and stuff.
What are your thoughts
on work-life balance
throughout a human lifetime?
So Tesla in part was
known for pushing people
to their limits, in terms
of what they're able to do,
in terms of what they're trying to do,
in terms of how much they
work, all that kind of stuff.
- Yeah, I mean I will say Tesla
gets a little too much bad rep for this
because what's happening is Tesla,
it's a bursty environment.
So I would say the baseline,
my only point of reference is Google
where I've interned three times
and I saw what it's like
inside Google and DeepMind,
I would say the baseline
is higher than that.
But then there's a punctual equilibrium
where once in a while there's a fire
and people work really hard
and so it's spiky and bursty
and then all the stories get collected-
- [Lex] Above the bursts.
Yeah.
- And then it gives the
appearance of total insanity.
But actually, it's just a
bit more intense environment
and there are fires and sprints
and so I think definitely
though I would say
it's a more intense environment
than something you would get at Google.
- But in your personal,
forget all of that,
just in your own personal life,
what do you think about the
happiness of a human being?
A brilliant person like yourself.
about finding a balance
between work and life
or is such a thing not a
good thought experiment?
- Yeah, I think balance is good
but I also love to have sprints
that are out of distribution
and that's when I think I've
been pretty creative as well.
- So sprints out of distribution
means that most of the time
you have a quote-unquote balance.
- I have balance most of the
time and I like being obsessed
with something once in a while.
- Once in a while is what, once a week,
once a month, once a year?
- Yeah.
Probably I'd like say
once a month or something.
Yeah.
- And that's when we get and
you get Git-Repo for market.
- Yeah.
That's when you're like
really care about a problem,
it must exist.
This will be awesome.
You're obsessed with it and
now you can't just do it
on that day, you need
to pay the fixed cost
of getting into the groove.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And then you need to
stay there for a while
and then society will come
and they will try to mess with you
and they will try to distract you.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- Yeah.
The worst thing is a person who's like,
"I just need five minutes of your time."
- [Lex] Yeah.
- The cost of that is not five minutes.
- [Lex] Yes.
- And society needs to
change how it thinks about
just five minutes of your time.
- Right.
It's never just one minute, just 30.
Just a quick thing.
- [Andrej] What's the big deal?
Why are you being, so?
- Yeah, no.
What's your computer setup?
What's like the perfect-
Are you somebody that's flexible
to no matter what laptop, four screens?
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Or do you prefer a certain setup
that you're most productive with?
- I guess the one that I'm familiar with
is one large screen, 27-inch
and my laptop on the side.
- What operating system?
- I do MaX, that's my primary.
- For all tasks?
- I would say OS X.
But when you're working on deep-learning,
everything is Linux,
you're SSH into a cluster
and you're working remotely.
- But what about the actual development?
Like using the IDE?
- Yeah.
You would use, I think a good
way is you just run VS Code,
my favorite editor right now on your Mac.
But you are actually, you have
a remote folder through SSH.
So the actual files
that you're manipulating
are on a cluster somewhere else.
- So what's the best IDE, VS Code?
What else do people use?
So I use Emax, still.
- That's old school.
- It may be cool, I don't know
if it's maximum productivity.
So what do you recommend
in terms of editors?
You worked with a lot
of software engineers,
editors for Python, C++,
machine learning applications.
- I think the current answer is VS Code,
currently, I believe that's the best IDE.
It's got a huge amount of extensions.
It has GitHub Copilot integration,
which I think is very valuable.
- What do you think about
the Copilot integration?
I got to talk a bunch
with Guido van Rossum
who's the creator of Python
and he loves Copilot,
he programs a lot with it.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Do you?
- Yeah, I use Copilot.
I love it.
And it's free for me
but I would pay for it.
Yeah.
I think it's very good.
And the utility that I found with it was,
I would say there's a learning curve
and you need to figure
out when it's helpful
and when to pay attention to its outputs
and when it's not going to be helpful
where you should not pay attention to it.
Because if you're just reading
its suggestions all the time,
it's not a good way of
interacting with it.
But I think I was able to
sort of mold myself to it.
I find it's very helpful,
number one, in copy-paste
and replace some parts.
So when the pattern is clear,
it's really good at
completing the pattern.
And number two, sometimes it suggests APIs
that I'm not aware of.
So it tells you about
something that you didn't know.
- And that's an opportunity
to discover a new thing.
- It's an opportunity to.
So I would never take
Copilot code as given.
I almost always copy-paste
into a Google search
and you see what this function is doing
and then you're like, "Oh,
that's actually exactly
what I need."
Thank you, Copilot.
So you learn something.
- So it's in part of search engine,
in part maybe getting the
exact syntax correctly
that once you see it, it's that MPR thing.
Once you see it, you know it's correct.
- [Andrej] Yes, exactly.
Exactly.
- You, yourself can struggle.
- [Andrej] You can verify.
- You can verify efficiently
but you can't generate efficiently.
- And Copilot really, I mean
it's autopilot for programming.
Right?
And currently is doing the link following
which is the simple copy-paste
and sometimes suggest,
but over time it's going to
become more and more autonomous.
And so the same thing will
play out in not just coding
but actually across many, many
different things probably.
- But coding is an important one, right?
- [Andrej] Very.
- Like writing programs.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- How do you see the
future of that developing
the program synthesis, like
being able to write programs
that are more and more complicated?
'Cause right now it's
human-supervised in interesting ways.
- [Andrej] Yes.
- It feels like the transition
will be very painful.
- My mental model for it is
the same thing will happen
as with the autopilot.
So currently, he's doing lane following,
he is doing some simple
stuff, and eventually,
we'll be doing autonomy
and people will have to
intervene less and less.
And those could be like
testing mechanisms.
If it writes a function
and that function looks
pretty damn correct.
But how do you know it's correct
'cause you're like
getting lazier and lazier
as a programmer, your ability
to, 'cause like little bugs
but I guess it won't make little mistakes.
- No it will, Copilot will make off
by one subtle bug.
It has done that to me.
- But do you think future systems will
or is it really the off by one
is actually a fundamental
challenge of programming.
- In that case it wasn't fundamental
and I think things can improve but yeah,
I think humans have to supervise.
I am nervous about people not
supervising what comes out
and what happens to, for example,
the proliferation of bugs
in all of our systems.
I'm nervous about that but I
think there will probably be
some other Copilots for bug finding
and stuff like that, at some point.
'Cause there'll be a
lot more automation for-
- Oh man, a Copilot that
generates a compiler,
one that does a linter.
- [Andrej] Yes.
- One that does like a type checker.
- Yeah.
It's a committee of a GPT sort of like-
- And then there'll be like
a manager for the committee.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- And then there'll be somebody that says,
a new version of this is needed.
We need to regenerate it.
- Yeah.
There were 10 GPTs that were forwarded
and gave 50 suggestions.
Another one looked at it and picked a few
that they like, a bug one looked at it
and it was like, it's probably
a bug, they got re-ranked
by some other thing and then
a final ensemble GPT comes in
and is like, okay, given
everything you guys have told me,
this is probably the next token.
- You know the feeling is
the number of programmers
in the world has been growing
and growing very quickly.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Do you think it's possible
that it'll actually level out
and drop to a very low
number in this kind of world?
'Cause then you'll be doing
Software 2.0 programming
and you'll be doing this generation
of Copilot-type systems programming.
But you won't be doing the old school
Software 1.0 programming.
- I don't currently think
that they're just going to
replace human programmers.
I'm so hesitant saying
stuff like this, right?
- Yeah.
Because this is gonna be
replayed in five years and no,
it's going to show that like
this is where we thought,
because I agree with you
but I think we might be
very surprised, right?
What's your sense of where we
stand with language models?
Does it feel like the beginning,
or the middle, or the end?
- The beginning, a hundred percent.
I think the big question in my mind is
for sure GPT will be able
to program quite well,
competently and so on.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- How do you steer the system?
You still have to provide some guidance
to what you actually are looking for.
And so how do you steer
it and how do you say,
how do you talk to it?
How do you audit it and verify
that what it's done is correct
and how do you work with this?
And it's as much not just an AI problem
but a UI, UX problem.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- So beautiful fertile ground
for so much interesting work
for VS Code++ where you're not just,
it's not just human programming anymore.
It's amazing.
- Yeah.
So you're interacting with the system
so not just one prompt but
it's iterative prompting.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- You're trying to figure
out, having a conversation
with the system.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- That actually, I mean to
me that's super exciting
to have a conversation with
the program I'm writing.
- Yeah.
Yeah.
Maybe at some point you're
just conversing with it.
It's like, okay, here's what I wanna do,
actually this variable.
Maybe it's not even that
low-level as a variable, but.
- You can also imagine
like can you translate
this to C++ and back
to Python and back to?
- Yeah, that already kind
of exists in some way.
- No, but just like doing it as part
of the program experience.
Like I think I'd like to
write this function in C++
or you just keep changing
from different programs
'cause of the different syntax,
maybe I want to convert this
into a functional language.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- And so you get to become
multilingual as a programmer
and dance back and forth efficiently.
- Yeah.
I mean I think the UI, UX of it though
is still very hard to think through.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- Because it's not just
about writing code on a page.
You have an entire developer environment,
you have a bunch of hardware on it,
you have some environmental variables,
you have some scripts that
are running in a Chrome job.
There's a lot going on
to working with computers
and how do these systems
set up environment flags,
and work across multiple machines,
and set up screen sessions,
and automate different processes.
like how all that works and is
auditable by humans and so on
is like massive question at the moment.
- You've built arxiv-sanity.
What is arxiv and what is the future
of academic research publishing
that you would like to see?
- So arxiv is this pre-print server.
So if you have a paper you
can submit it for publication
to journals or conferences
and then wait six months
and then maybe get a
decision pass or fail,
or you can just upload it to arxiv
and then people can Tweet
about it three minutes later.
And then everyone sees
it, everyone reads it,
and everyone can profit from
it in their own little ways.
- And you can cite it and it
has an official look to it.
It feels like a publication process.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- It feels different than if
you just put in a blog post.
- Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
I mean it's a paper and
usually the bar is higher
for something that you
would expect on arxiv
as opposed to something you
would see in a blog post.
- Well, the culture created the bar
'cause you could probably post
a pretty crappy paper or an arxiv.
- [Andrej] Yes.
- So what's that make you feel like,
what's that make you
feel about peer review?
So rigorous peer review
by two, three experts
versus the peer review
of the community right
as it's written?
- Yeah.
Basically, I think the
community is very well able
to peer-review things
very quickly on Twitter.
And I think maybe it
just has to do something
with AI machine learning
field specifically though,
I feel like things are
more easily auditable
and the verification is easier potentially
than the verification somewhere else.
So it's like, you can think of these
scientific publications
as little block-chains
where everyone's building
on each other's work
and citing each other
and you sort of have AI,
which is this much faster
and loose blockchain,
but then you have, and
any one individual entry
is very cheap to make.
And then you have other
fields where maybe that model
doesn't make as much sense.
And so I think in AI at least
things are pretty easily verifiable.
And so that's why when
people upload papers,
they have a really good idea and so on.
People can try it out the next day
and they can be the final arbiter
of whether it works or not
on their problem.
And the whole thing just
moves significantly faster.
So I feel like academia still has a place,
sorry, this conference, journal
process still has a place,
but it's sort of it lags behind I think,
and it's a bit more maybe
higher quality process.
But it's not the place
where you will discover
cutting-edge work anymore.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- It used to be the case
when I was starting my PhD
that you go to conferences and journals
and you discuss all the latest research.
Now when you go to a
conference or a journal,
no one discusses anything that's there
because it's already like three
generations ago, irrelevant.
- Yes.
Which makes me sad about
like DeepMind for example,
where they still publish in nature
and these big prestigious,
I mean there's still value,
I suppose to the prestige that
comes with these big venues.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- But the result is that they'll announce
some breakthrough performance
and it'll take like a year to
actually publish the details.
I mean, and those details,
if they were published
immediately would inspire
the community to move in
certain directions, would they?
- Yeah.
It would speed up the
rest of the community,
but I don't know to what
extent that's part of their
objective function also.
- That's true.
So it's not just the prestige.
A little bit of the delay is part.
- Yeah, they certainly,
DeepMind specifically,
has been working in the regime
of having slightly higher
quality basically process
and latency and publishing
those papers that way.
- Another question from Reddit.
Do you or have you suffered
from imposter syndrome,
being the director of AI
Tesla, being this person
when you're at Stanford
where the world looks at you
as the expert in AI to teach the world
about machine learning.
- When I was leaving
Tesla after five years,
I spent a ton of time in meeting rooms
and I would read papers.
In the beginning, when I joined
Tesla, I was writing code
and then I was writing less and less code,
and I was reading code
and then I was reading
less and less code.
And so this is just a natural progression
that happens I think.
And definitely, I would
say near the tail end,
that's when it starts
to hit you a bit more.
That you're supposed to be an expert
but actually, the source
of truth is the code
that people are writing, the GitHub
and the actual code itself.
And you're not as familiar
with that as you used to be.
And so I would say maybe
there's some insecurity there.
- Yeah, that's actually pretty profound,
that a lot of the insecurity has to do
with not writing the code
in the computer science space
'cause that is the truth.
That right there.
- The code is the source of truth.
The papers and everything else,
it's a high-level summary.
I don't, yeah, just a high-level summary,
but at the end of the day
you have to read code.
It's impossible to translate all that code
into actual paper form.
So when things come out,
especially when they have
a source code available,
that's my favorite place to go.
- So like I said, you're
one of the greatest teachers
of machine learning AI
ever from CS231n to today,
what advice would you give to beginners
interested in getting
into machine learning?
- Beginners are often
focused on what to do
and I think the focus should
be more how much you do.
So I am a believer on the high-level,
in this 10,000 hours concept
where you just have to
just pick the things
where you can spend time
and you care about and
you're interested in.
You literally have to put
in 10,000 hours of work.
It doesn't even matter
as much where you put it,
you'll iterate and you'll improve
and you'll waste some time.
I dunno if there's a better way.
You need to put in 10,000 hours.
But I think it's actually really nice
'cause I feel like there's
some sense of determinism
about being an expert at a thing
if you spend 10,000 hours.
you can literally pick an arbitrary thing
and I think if you spend 10,000 hours
of deliberate effort and work,
you actually will become an expert at it.
And so I think it's like a nice thought.
And so basically I would focus more on
are you spending 10,000 hours?
That's what I would focus on.
- And then thinking about what
kind of mechanisms maximize
your likelihood of
getting to 10,000 hours.
- [Andrej] Yes, exactly.
- Which for us silly humans
means probably forming
a daily habit of every single
day actually doing thing.
- Whatever helps you.
So I do think to a large extent
it's a psychological problem for yourself.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- One other thing that I think is helpful
for the psychology of it,
is many times people compare themselves
to others in the area, I
think this very harmful.
Only compare yourself to
you from some time ago.
Like say a year ago, are you
better than you a year ago?
This is the only way to think.
And I think then you can see your progress
and it's very motivating.
- That's so interesting.
That focus on the quantity of hours.
'Cause I think a lot of
people in the beginner stage
but actually throughout get
paralyzed by the choice.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Like which one do I pick
this path or this path?
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- They'll literally get
paralyzed by which IDE to use?
- Well, they're worried, yeah,
they'll worried about all these things.
But the thing is, you will waste
time doing something wrong.
- [Lex] Yes.
- You will eventually
figure out it's not right.
You will accumulate scar tissue
and next time you'll grow stronger
because next time you'll
have the scar tissue,
and next time you'll learn from it.
And now next time you come
to a similar situation
you'll be like, oh, I messed up.
I've spent a lot of time working on things
that never materialized into anything
and I have all that scar tissue
and I have some intuitions
about what was useful,
what wasn't useful, how things turned out.
So all those mistakes were not dead work.
So I just think they should
just focus on working.
What have you done, what
have you done last week?
- That's a good question actually
to ask for a lot of things,
not just machine learning.
It's a good way to cut the,
I forgot the term we use,
but the fluff, the blubber,
whatever the inefficiencies in life.
What do you love about teaching?
You seem to find yourself often
in the, drawn to teaching.
You're very good at it but
you're also drawn to it.
- Yeah, I mean I don't
think I love teaching.
I love happy humans and happy
humans like when I teach.
- Yes.
- I wouldn't say I hate
teaching, I tolerate teaching.
- [Lex] Yes.
- But it's not like the act
of teaching that I like,
it's that I have something,
I'm actually okay at it.
- [Lex] Yes.
- I'm okay at teaching and
people appreciate it a lot.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And so I'm just happy
to try to be helpful
and teaching itself is not like the most,
I mean it can be really
annoying, frustrating.
I was working on a bunch
of lectures just now.
I was reminded back to my days of 231n
just how much work it is to
create some of these materials
and make them good.
The amount of iteration and thought
and you go down blind alleys
and just how much you change it.
So creating something good
in terms of educational value
is really hard and it's not fun.
- It's difficult.
So people should definitely
go watch your new stuff you put out.
There are lectures where you're
actually building the thing,
like you said, "The code is truth."
So discussing back-propagation
by building it,
by looking through and
just the whole thing.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- So how difficult is that to prepare for?
I think that's a really
powerful way to teach.
Did you have to prepare for that
or are you just live thinking through it?
- I will typically do like say three takes
and then I take the better take.
So I do multiple takes and I
take some of the better takes
and then I just build
out a lecture that way.
Sometimes I have to delete
30 minutes of content.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- Because it just went down the alley
that I didn't like too much.
So there's about a bunch of iteration
and it probably takes me
somewhere around 10 hours
to create one hour of content.
- To get one hour.
It's interesting.
I mean is it difficult
to go back to the basics?
Do you draw a lot of wisdom
from going back to the basics?
- Yeah, going back to
backropagation, loss functions,
where they come from.
And one thing I like about
teaching a lot honestly is
it definitely strengthens
your understanding.
So it's not a purely altruistic activity,
it's a way to learn.
If you have to explain
something to someone,
you realize you have gaps in knowledge.
And so I even surprised
myself in those lectures like,
well, the result will
obviously look like this
and then the result doesn't look like it.
And I'm like, okay, I
thought I understood this.
- Yeah.
Well, that's why it's really
cool, they literally code,
you run it in the notebook
and it gives you a result
and you're like, oh, wow.
- [Andrej] Yes.
- And like actual numbers,
actual input, actual code.
- Yeah.
It's not mathematical symbols, et cetera.
The source of truth is the code.
It's not slides, it's
just like let's build it.
- It's beautiful.
You're a rare human in that sense.
What advice would you give to researchers
trying to develop and publish an idea
that have a big impact in the world of AI?
So maybe undergrads, maybe
early-graduate students.
- Yeah.
I mean I would say they
definitely have to be
a little bit more
strategic than I had to be
as a PhD student because
of the way AI is evolving,
it's going the way of physics.
Where in physics you used
to be able to do experiments
on your bench-top and everything was great
and you could make progress
and now you have to work
in like LHC or like CERN and so AI
is going in that direction as well.
So there's certain kinds of things
that's just not possible to
do on the bench-top anymore.
And I think that didn't used
to be the case at the time.
- Do you still think that
there's like GAN type papers
to be written where like very simple idea.
- [Andrej] Yes.
- That requires just one computer
to illustrate a simple example?
- I mean one example that's
been very influential recently
is diffusion models,
diffusion models are amazing.
Diffusion models are six years old.
For the longest time,
people were ignoring them
as far as I can tell.
And they're an amazing generative model,
especially in images and so
stable diffusion and so on,
it's all diffusion-based.
Diffusion is new, it was
not there and it came from,
well, it came from Google but a researcher
could have come up with it.
In fact, some of the first, actually no,
those came from Google as well.
But a researcher could come up with that
in an academic institution.
- Yeah.
What do you find most fascinating
about diffusion models?
So from the societal impact
of the technical architecture.
- What I like about diffusion
is it works so well.
- Is that surprising to you?
The amount of the variety,
almost the novelty
of the synthetic data it's generating?
- Yeah, so the stable diffusion
images are incredible.
It's the speed of improvement
in generating images
has been insane.
We went very quickly from
generating tiny digits
to tiny faces and it all looked messed up.
And now we have stable diffusion
and that happened very quickly.
There's a lot that academia
can still contribute.
For example, FlashAttention
is a very efficient kernel
for running the attention
operation inside the transformer
that came from academic environment.
It's a very clever way
to structure the kernel,
that's the calculation.
So it doesn't materialize
the attention matrix.
And so, I think there's
still like lots of things
to contribute but you have
to be just more strategic.
- Do you think neural networks
could be made to reason?
- Yes.
- Do you think they already reason?
- [Lex] What's your
definition of reasoning?
- Information processing.
- So in the way that humans
think through a problem
and come up with novel ideas,
it feels like a reasoning.
- Yeah.
- So the novelty, I don't wanna say
but auto-distribution ideas,
you think it's possible?
- Yes.
And I think we're seeing that already
in the current neural nets.
You're able to remix the
training set information
into true generalization in some sense.
- That doesn't appear-
- It doesn't appear verbatim
in the training set.
You're doing something
interesting algorithmically,
you're manipulating some symbols
and you're coming up with
some correct unique answer
in a new setting.
- What would illustrate to you, holy shit,
this thing is definitely thinking?
- To me thinking or reasoning
is just information
processing and generalization.
And I think the neural
nets already do that today.
- So being able to perceive the world
or perceive the, whatever the inputs are
and to make predictions based on that
or actions based on that's reasoning?
- Yeah.
You're giving correct
answers in novel settings
by manipulating information.
You've learned the correct algorithm,
you're not doing just some
kind of a lookup table
and nearest neighbor search.
Something like that.
- Let me ask you about AGI.
What are some moonshot ideas
you think might make
significant progress towards AGI
and maybe another way is,
what are the big blockers
that we're missing now?
- So basically, I am fairly
bullish on our ability
to build AGIs, basically automated systems
that we can interact with
that are very human-like
and we can interact with them
in a digital realm or a physical realm.
Currently, it seems most of the models
that do these magical
tasks are in a text realm.
I think, as I mentioned, I'm
suspicious that text realm
is not enough to actually
build full understanding
of the world.
I do actually think you
need to go into pixels
and understand the physical
world and how it works.
So I do think that we need
to extend these models
to consume images and videos
and train on a lot more data
that is multimodal in that way.
- Do you think you need to touch the world
to understand it also?
- Well, that's the big open question
I would say in my mind,
is if you also require
the embodiment and the ability
to interact with the world,
run experiments and have
a data of that form,
then you need to go to Optimus
or something like that.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And so I would say Optimus
in some way is like a hedge
in AGI because it seems
to me that it's possible
that just having data from
the internet is not enough.
If that is the case, then
Optimus may lead to AGI.
Because Optimus would, to me,
there's nothing beyond Optimus.
You have like this humanoid form factor
that can actually do stuff in the world.
You can have millions of them
interacting with humans and so on.
And if that doesn't give a
rise to AGI at some point,
I'm not sure what will.
So from a completeness perspective,
I think that's a really good platform
but it's a much more harder platform
because you are dealing with atoms
and you need to actually
build these things
and integrate them into society.
So I think that path takes longer
but it's much more certain.
And then there's a path of the internet
and just training these
compression models effectively
on trying to compress all the internet.
And that might also give
these agents as well.
- Compress the internet but
also interact with the internet.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- So it's not obvious to me.
In fact, I suspect you can reach AGI
without ever entering the physical world,
which is a little bit more concerning
because that results
in it happening faster.
So it just feels like
we're in boiling water.
We won't know as it's happening.
I would like to, I'm not afraid of AGI,
I'm excited about it.
There's always concerns
but I would like to know when it happens.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- And have like hints
about when it happens,
like a year from now it will
happen, that kind of thing.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- I just feel like in the digital realm
it just might happen.
- Yeah.
I think all we have available to us
because no one has built AGI again,
so all we have available to us is,
is there enough fertile
ground on the periphery?
I would say, yes.
And we have the progress so far,
which has been very rapid
and there are next steps
that are available.
And so I would say,
yeah, it's quite likely
that we'll be interacting
with digital entities.
- How will you know that
somebody has built AGI?
- I think it's going to be a
slow incremental transition.
It's going to be
product-based and focused.
It's going to be GitHub
Copilot going better.
And then GPTs helping you
write and then these oracles
that you can go to with
mathematical problems.
I think we're on a verge of being able
to ask very complex questions
in chemistry, physics,
math of these oracles and
have them complete solutions.
- So AGI to use primarily
focused on intelligence
so consciousness doesn't enter into it.
- So in my mind, consciousness
is not a special thing
you will figure out and bolt on.
I think it's an emergent
phenomenon of a large enough
and complex enough
generative model sort of.
So if you have a complex
enough world model
that understands the world,
then it also understands
its predicament in the world
as being a language model,
which to me is a form of
consciousness or self-awareness.
- So in order to
understand the world deeply
you probably have to integrate
yourself into the world.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- And in order to interact with humans
and other living beings,
consciousness is a very useful tool.
- Yeah.
I think consciousness is
like a modeling insight.
- Modeling insight.
- Yeah.
You have a powerful enough model
of understanding the world
that you actually understand
that you are an entity in it.
- Yeah.
But there's also this,
perhaps just a narrative
we tell ourselves, it feels like something
to experience the world, the
hard problem of consciousness.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- But that could be just a
narrative that we tell ourselves.
- Yeah.
I don't think we'll, yeah,
I think it will emerge.
I think it's going to be
something very boring.
We'll be talking to these digital AIs,
they will claim they're conscious,
they will appear conscious,
they will do all the things
that you would expect of other humans
and it's going to just be a stalemate.
- I think there will be a lot
of actual fascinating ethical questions,
like supreme court level questions
of whether you're allowed
to turn off a conscious AI,
if you're allowed to build a conscious AI,
maybe there would have to
be the same kind of debates
that you have around, sorry
to bring up a political topic,
but abortion, which is the
deeper question with abortion
is what is life?
And the deep question with AI is also,
what is life and what is conscious?
- [Andrej] Right.
- And I think that'll be very fascinating
to bring up, it might become
illegal to build systems
that are capable of such
level of intelligence
that consciousness would emerge
and therefore the capacity
to suffer would emerge.
And a system that says,
no, please don't kill me.
- Well, that's what the
LaMDA chatbot already told
this Google engineer, right?
It was talking about not
wanting to die or so on.
- So that might become illegal to do that.
- [Andrej] Right.
- 'Cause otherwise, you
might have a lot of creatures
that don't want to die and they will-
- [Andrej] You can just spawn
infinity of them on a cluster.
- And then that might lead
to horrible consequences.
'Cause then there might be a lot of people
that secretly love murder
and they'll start practicing
murder on those systems.
I mean there's just, to me
all of this stuff just brings
a beautiful mirror to the human condition
and human nature and we get to explore it.
- [Andrej] Yes.
- And that's what like the
best of the supreme court
of all the different
debates we have about ideas
of what it means to be human,
we get to those deep questions
that we've been asking
throughout human history.
There's always been the
other in human history.
We're the good guys
and that's the bad guys
and we're going to
throughout human history,
let's murder the bad guys.
And the same will probably
happen with robots.
It'll be the other at first.
And then we'll get to ask questions,
that what does it mean to be alive?
What does it mean to be conscious?
- Yep.
And I think there's some
canary in the coal mines
even with what we have today.
And for example, there's these waifus
that you can work with
and some people are trying to,
this company's going to shut down,
but this person really loved their waifu
and is trying to like
port it somewhere else.
And it's not possible.
And I think definitely
people will have feelings
towards these systems
because in some sense
they are like a mirror of humanity
because they are like a
big average of humanity.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- In a way that it's trained.
- But that average, we can actually watch.
It's nice to be able to interact
with the big average of humanity.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- And do a search query on it.
- Yeah.
Yeah.
It's very fascinating.
And we can also of course, also shape it.
It's not just a pure average.
We can mess with the training data,
we can mess with the objective,
we can fine-tune them in various ways.
So we have some impact on
what those systems look like.
- If you want to achieve AGI
and you could have a conversation with her
and ask her, talk about anything,
maybe ask her a question.
What kind of stuff would you ask?
- I would've some practical
questions in my mind
like do I or my loved
ones really have to die?
What can we do about that?
- Do you think it will answer clearly
or would it answer poetically?
- I would expect it to give solutions.
I would expect it to be
like, well, I've read
all of these textbooks and
I know all these things
that you've produced and it seems to me
like here are the experiments
that I think it would
be useful to run next.
And here are some gene therapies
that I think would be helpful,
and here are the kinds of
experiments that you should run.
- Okay, let's go with
this thought experiment.
Okay.
Imagine that mortality is actually
a prerequisite for happiness.
So if we become immortal,
we'll actually become deeply unhappy
and the model is able to know that.
So what is it supposed to tell you?
A stupid human about it?
Yes, you can become a mortal
but you'll become deeply unhappy.
If the AGI system is trying
to empathize with you human,
what is it supposed to tell you.
That yes, you don't have to die
but you're really not gonna like it?
Is it gonna be deeply honest?
There's an "Interstellar",
what is it the AI says like
humans want 90% honesty.
So you have to pick how honest
do I want to answer these
practical questions?
- Yeah.
I love AI "Interstellar" by the way.
I think it's like such a
sidekick to the entire story
but at the same time,
it's really interesting.
- It's kind of limited
in certain ways, right?
- Yeah, it's limited and I
think that's totally fine
by the way.
I think it's fine and
plausible to have a limited
and imperfect AGIs.
- Is that a feature almost?
- As an example, it has
a fixed amount of compute
on its physical body.
And it might just be that
even though you can have
a super amazing mega brain,
super-intelligent AI,
you also can have less intelligent AI
that you can deploy in
a power-efficient way.
And then they're not perfect,
they might make mistakes.
- No, I meant more like say
you had infinite compute
and it's still good to
make mistakes sometimes.
In order to integrate yourself.
Like, what is it?
Going back to "Goodwill Hunting",
Robin Williams character
says the human imperfections,
that's good stuff, right?
We don't want perfect,
we want flaws in part to form
connections with each other.
'Cause it feels like
something you can attach
your feelings to, the flaws.
In that same way you
want an AI that's flawed.
I don't know.
I feel like perfection is cold.
- [Andrej] Okay, yeah.
- But that's not AGI.
But see AGI would need
to be intelligent enough
to give answers to humans
that humans don't understand.
And I think perfect is something
humans can't understand
because even science doesn't
give perfect answers.
There's always gaps and
mysteries and I don't know,
I don't know if humans want perfect.
- Yeah, I could imagine
just having a conversation
with this oracle entity
as you'd imagine them
and yeah, maybe it can tell you about,
based on my analysis of human condition,
you might not want this
and here are some of
the things that might-
- But every dumb human will
say, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah,
trust me, give me the
truth, I can handle it.
- But that's the beauty,
like people can choose.
- But then, it's the old marshmallow test
with the kids and so on, I
feel like too many people
can't handle the truth,
probably including myself.
Deep truth to the human condition.
I don't know if I can handle it.
What if there's some dark stuff?
What if we are an alien science experiment
and it realizes that.
What if it hacked, I mean?
- I mean, this is "The
Matrix" all over again.
- "The Matrix", I don't know,
what would I talk about?
I don't even, yeah, probably I will go
with the safer scientific
questions at first
that have nothing to do
with my own personal life.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Immortality just like
about physics and so on.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- To build up see where it's at
or maybe see if it has a sense of humor.
That's another question.
Presumably in order to, if
it understands humans deeply,
would it able to generate humor.
- Yeah.
I think that's actually a
wonderful benchmark almost,
like is it able, I think that's
a really good point, basically.
- [Lex] To make you laugh.
- Yeah.
If it's able to be a very
effective standup comedian
that is doing something very
interesting computationally.
I think being funny is extremely hard.
- Yeah, because it's hard in
a way like a touring test,
the original intent of
the touring test is hard
because you have to convince humans
and that's why comedians talk about this,
like this is deeply honest.
'Cause if people can't help but laugh
and if they don't laugh
that means you're not funny,
if they laugh, it's funny.
- Yeah.
And you're showing, you
need a lot of knowledge
to create humor about like you mentioned
human condition and so on.
And then you need to be clever with it.
- You mentioned a few movies,
you Tweeted, "Movies that
I've seen five-plus times
but am ready and willing to keep watching:
'Interstellar', 'Gladiator',
'Contact', 'Goodwill Hunting',
'The Matrix', 'Lord of
the Rings', all three,
'Avatar', 'Fifth Element'," and so on,
it goes on, "'Terminator 2'."
"Mean Girls" I'm not
gonna ask about that one.
- "Mean Girls" is great.
- What are some that jump out to you
in your memory that you love and why?
You mentioned "The Matrix"
as a computer person,
why do you love "The Matrix"?
- There's so many properties
that make it beautiful and interesting.
So there's all these
philosophical questions
but then there's also AGIs,
and there's simulation,
and it's cool, and there's the black.
- [Lex] The look of it, the feel of it.
- Yeah.
The look of it, the feel of it,
the action, the bullet time.
It was just like
innovating in so many ways.
- And then "Goodwill Hunting".
Why do you like that one?
- Yeah, I really like this
tortured genius character
who's grappling with whether or not
he has any responsibility or what to do
with this gift that he was given
or how to think about the whole thing and-
- But there's also a
dance between the genius
and the personal, like what it means
to love another human being.
- Yeah.
There's a lot of themes there.
It's just a beautiful movie.
- And then the fatherly figure,
the mentor and the psychiatrist.
- It really messes with you.
There's some movies that just
like really mess with you
on a deep level.
- Do you relate to that movie at all?
- No.
- It's not your fault Andrej, as I said.
"Lord of the Rings",
that's self-explanatory.
"Terminator 2", which is interesting,
you rewatch that a lot.
Is that better than Terminator one?
You don't like Arnold as he comes back?
- I do like Terminator one as well.
I like "Terminator 2" a little bit more.
But in terms of its surface properties.
- Do you think Skynet
is at all a possibility?
- Yes.
- Like the actual autonomous
weapon system kind of thing?
Do you worry about that stuff?
So AI being used for war?
- I a hundred percent worry about it.
And so the, I mean, some
of these fears of AGIs
and how this will plan
out, I mean these will be
very powerful entities
probably at some point.
And so for a long time,
there are going to be tools
in the hands of humans.
People talk about alignment of AGIs
and how to make, the problem
is even humans are not aligned.
So how this will be used and
what this is gonna look like
is, yeah, it's troubling.
- Do you think it'll happen slowly enough
that we'll be able to
as a human civilization
think through the problems?
- Yes, that's my hope, is
that it happens slowly enough
and in an open enough way
where a lot of people can see
and participate in it.
Just to figure out how to
deal with this transition,
I think, which is gonna be interesting.
- I draw a lot of inspiration
from nuclear weapons
'cause I sure thought it would be fucked
once they develop nuclear weapons.
But it's almost like when the
systems are not so dangerous
they destroy human civilization.
We deploy them and learn the
lessons and then we quickly,
if it's too dangerous we quickly, quickly,
we might still deploy it
but you very quickly learn
not to use them.
And so there'll be like
this balance achieved,
humans are very clever as a species.
It's interesting, we exploit
the resources as much as we can
but we avoid destroying
ourselves it seems like.
- Yeah.
Well, I dunno about that actually.
- I hope it continues.
- I mean I'm definitely like concerned
about nuclear weapons and so on,
not just as a result
of the recent conflict,
even before that.
That's probably like my number
one concern for humanity.
- So if humanity destroys
itself or destroys 90% of people
that would be because of nukes?
- Yeah, I think so.
And it's not even about full destruction,
to me, it's bad enough
if we reset society,
that would be terrible.
That would be really bad.
And I can't believe we're so close to it.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- It's like so crazy to me.
- It feels like we might
be a few Tweets away
from something like that.
- Yep.
Basically, it's extremely unnerving
and has been for me for a long time.
- It seems unstable that world leaders
just having a bad mood can take one step
towards a bad direction
and then it escalates.
- Yeah.
- And because of a
collection of bad moods,
it can escalate without
being able to stop.
- Yeah.
It's a huge amount of power.
And then also with the proliferation
and basically, I don't
actually really see,
I don't actually know what
the good outcomes are here,
so I'm definitely
worried about that a lot.
And then AGI is not currently there
but I think at some point
it will more and more become
something like it.
The danger with AGI even is that
I think it's even slightly worse
in the sense that there
are good outcomes of AGI
and then the bad outcomes
are an epsilon way,
like a tiny run away.
And so I think capitalism
and humanity, and so on
will drive for the positive
ways of using that technology.
But then if bad outcomes
are just like a tiny,
like flip a minus sign away,
that's a really bad position to be in.
- A tiny perturbation of the system
results in the destruction
of the human species.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- It's a weird line to walk.
- Yeah, I think in general
what's really weird
about the dynamics of humanity
and this explosion we talked about
is just the insane coupling
afforded by technology.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And just the instability of
the whole dynamical system.
I think it doesn't look good, honestly.
- Yes.
That explosion could be
destructive or constructive
and the probabilities are
non-zero in both ends of it.
- I'm gonna have to, I
do feel like I have to
try to be optimistic and so on
and I think even in this case
I still am predominantly
optimistic but there's definitely-
- Me too.
Do you think we'll become
a multi-planetary species?
- Probably, yes.
But I don't know if it's dominant feature
of future humanity.
There might be some people
on some planets and so on
but I'm not sure if it's like, yeah,
if it's like a major player
in our culture and so on.
- We still have to solve the drivers
of self-destruction here on earth.
So just having a backup on Mars
is not gonna solve the problem.
- So by the way, I love
the backup on Mars.
I think that's amazing.
We should absolutely do that.
- [Lex] Yes.
- And I'm so thankful.
- Would you go to Mars?
- Personally, no, I do
like earth quite a lot.
- Okay.
I'll go to Mars.
I'll go for you.
I'll Tweet at you from there.
- Maybe eventually I would,
once it's safe enough.
But I don't actually know
if it's on my lifetime scale
unless I can extend it by a lot.
I do think that for example, a
lot of people might disappear
into virtual realities and stuff like that
and I think that could be the major thrust
of the cultural development
of humanity if it survives.
So it might not be, it's
just really hard to work
in physical realm and go out there
and I think ultimately
all your experiences
are in your brain.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And so it's much easier to
disappear into digital realm
and I think people will find
them more compelling, easier,
safer, more interesting.
- So you're a little bit
captivated by virtual reality,
by the possible worlds,
whether it's the metaverse
or some other manifestation of that?
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Yeah.
It's really interesting.
I'm interested, just
talking a lot to Carmack,
where's the thing that's
currently preventing that?
- Yeah, I mean to be clear,
I think what's interesting
about the future is it's
not that, I feel like
the variance in the human condition grows.
That's the primary thing that's changing.
It's not as much the
mean of the distribution,
it's like the variance of it.
So there will probably be people on Mars
and there will be people in VR,
and there will people here on earth.
It's just like there will be
so many more ways of being.
And so feel like, I see
it as like a spreading out
of a human experience.
- There's something about the internet
that allows you to discover
those little groups
and you gravitate to,
something about your biology
likes that kind of world
and you find each other.
- Yeah.
And we'll have trans-humanists
and then we'll have the Amish
and everything is just gonna coexist.
- Yeah.
The cool thing about it
'cause I've interacted
with a bunch of internet communities
is they don't know about each other.
Like you can have a very happy existence
just having a very close-knit community
and not knowing about each other.
I mean even you even sense this,
just having traveled to Ukraine,
they don't know so many
things about America.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- When you travel across the world
I think you experience this too.
There are certain cultures that are like,
they have their own thing
going on, they don't.
And so you can see that
happening more and more and more
and more in the future.
We have little communities.
- Yeah.
Yeah.
I think so.
That seems to be how it's going right now.
And I don't see that
trend really reversing.
I think people are
diverse and they're able
to choose their own path in
existence and I celebrate that.
And so-
- Will you spend some,
much time in the metaverse,
in the virtual reality?
Or which community are you,
are you the physicalist,
the physical reality enjoyer
or do you see drawing a lot
of pleasure and fulfillment
in the digital world?
- Yeah, I think, well
currently, the virtual reality
is not that compelling.
- [Lex] Yes.
- I do think it can improve a lot
but I don't really know to what extent.
Maybe there's actually
even more exotic things
you can think about with neural
links or stuff like that.
So currently, I kind of see
myself as mostly a team,
human person, I love nature.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- I love harmony, I love
people, I love humanity.
I love emotions of humanity
and I just want to be
in this solar punk little utopia.
That's my happy place.
- [Lex] Yes.
- My happy place is people I love,
thinking about cool problems,
surrounded by a lush,
beautiful dynamic nature.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And secretly high-tech
in places that count.
- Places that count.
So you use technology to empower that love
for other humans and nature.
- Yeah, I think a technology
used very sparingly.
I don't love when it gets
in the way of humanity
in many ways.
I like just people being humans
in a way, we slightly
evolved and prefer I think
just by default.
- People kept asking me 'cause
they know you love reading.
Are there particular
books that you enjoyed
that had an impact on you for silly
or for profound reasons
that you would recommend?
You mentioned "The Vital Question".
- Many, of course.
I think in biology as an example,
"The Vital Question" is a good one.
Anything by Nick Lane
really, "Life Ascending"
I would say is a bit more
potentially representative
as like a summary of a lot of the things
he's been talking about.
I was very impacted by "The Selfish Gene".
I thought that was a really good book,
it helped me understand
altruism as an example
and where it comes from.
And just realizing that the selection
and the levels of genes
was a huge insight for me at the time
and it cleared up a lot of things for me.
- What do you think about the idea
that ideas are the organisms, the memes?
- Yeah.
Love it.
A hundred percent.
- Are you able to walk around
with that notion for a while?
That there's an
evolutionary kind of process
with ideas as well?
- There absolutely is.
There's memes just like
genes and they compete
and they live in our brains.
It's beautiful.
- Are we silly humans thinking
that we are the organisms?
Is it possible that the primary
organisms are the ideas?
- Yeah, I would say like
the ideas kind of live
in the software of our
civilization in the minds
and so on.
We think as humans that the hardware
is the fundamental thing.
I human is a hardware entity.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- But it could be the software, right?
- Yeah.
Yeah.
I would say there needs
to be some grounding
at some point to a physical reality.
- Yeah, but if we clone an Andrej,
the software is a thing that
makes that thing special.
Right?
- Yeah.
I guess you're right.
- But then cloning might
be exceptionally difficult.
There might be a deep integration
between the software and the hardware
in ways we don't quite yet understand.
- Well, from the altruism point of view,
what makes me special is
more the gang of genes
that are riding in my
chromosomes I suppose.
Right?
They're the replicating unit I suppose-
- No, but that's just the compute,
the thing that makes you special, sure.
Well, the reality is
what makes you special
is your ability to survive
based on the software
that runs on the hardware
that was built by the genes.
So the software is the thing
that makes you survive.
Not the hardware or-
- It's a little bit of both.
It's just like a second layer.
It's a new second layer
that hasn't been there before the brain.
They both coexist.
- But there's also layers of the software.
I mean it's an abstraction
on top of abstractions.
Okay, "Selfish Gene".
- So "Selfish Gene", Nick Lane.
I would say sometimes
books are not sufficient.
I like to reach for textbooks sometimes.
I feel like books are for too much
of a general consumption sometime
and they're too high up in the level
of abstraction and it's not good enough.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- So I like textbooks, I like "The Cell".
I think "The Cell" was pretty cool.
That's why also I like
the writing of Nick Lane
is because he's pretty
willing to step one level down
and he doesn't, yeah,
he's willing to go there
but he's also willing to
be throughout the stack.
So he'll go down to a lot of detail
but then he will come back
up and I think he has a,
yeah, basically, I really appreciate that.
- That's why I love
college, early college,
even high school, just
textbooks on the basics
of computer science, of mathematics,
of biology, of chemistry.
- [Andrej] Yes.
- Those are, they condense
down, it's sufficient in general
that you can understand
both the philosophy
and the details but also
you get homework problems
and you get to play with
it as much as you would
if you were in programming stuff.
- Yeah.
And then I'm also suspicious
of textbooks honestly
because as an example in deep-learning
there's no amazing textbooks
and the field is changing very quickly.
I imagine the same is true
in say synthetic biology
and so on, these books like
"The Cell" are kind of outdated.
They're still high-level,
like what is the actual
real source of truth?
It's people in wet labs
working with cells.
- Yeah.
- Sequencing genomes and,
yeah, actually working with it.
And I don't have that
much exposure to that
or what that looks like.
So I still don't fully, I'm
reading through the cell
and it's kind of
interesting, and I'm learning
but it's still not sufficient I would say
in terms of understanding.
- Well, it's a clean summarization
of the mainstream narrative.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- But you have to learn
that before you break out.
- [Andrej] Yeah,
- Towards the cutting edge.
- Yeah.
But what is the actual process
of working with these cells
and growing them and incubating them
and it's like a massive cooking recipe.
So making sure your cell
slows and proliferate
and then you're sequencing
them, running experiments
and just how that works, I
think is the source of truth of
at the end of the day what's really useful
in terms of creating therapies and so on.
- Yeah.
I wonder what in the
future AI textbooks will be
'cause you know there's
"Artificial Intelligence:
A Modern Approach".
I actually haven't read, if it's come out,
the recent version, there's
been a recent edition.
I also saw there's a science
of deep learning book.
I'm waiting for textbooks
that are worth recommending,
worth reading.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- It's tricky 'cause it's like
papers and code, code, code.
- Honestly, I find papers are quite good.
I especially like the
appendix of any paper as well.
It's like the most detail you can have.
- It doesn't have to be cohesive,
connected to anything else.
You just described me a very specific way
you saw the particular thing.
Yeah.
- Yeah, many times papers can
be actually quite readable,
not always, but sometimes the
introduction and the abstract
is readable even for someone
outside of the field.
This is not always true
and sometimes I think,
unfortunately, scientists
use complex terms
even when it's not necessary.
I think that's harmful.
I think there's no reason for that.
- And papers sometimes are
longer than they need to be
in the parts that don't matter.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- The appendix should be long
but then the papers
itself, look at Einstein,
make it simple.
- Yeah.
But certainly, I've come
across papers I would say,
say like synthetic biology or something
that I thought were quite
readable for the abstract
and the introduction and then
you're reading the rest of it
and you don't fully understand
but you kind of are getting
a gist and I think it's cool.
- You give advice to folks
interested in machine learning
and research but in general life advice
to a young person, high
school, early college
about how to have a career
they can be proud of
or a life they can be proud of?
- Yeah, I think I'm very
hesitant to give general advice.
I think it's really hard.
I've mentioned, some of
the stuff I've mentioned
is fairly general, I think.
Like focus on just the amount
of work you're spending
on like a thing.
Compare yourself only to
yourself, not to others.
- [Lex] That's good.
- [Andrej] I think those
are fairly general.
- How do you pick the thing?
- You just have like a
deep interest in something
or try to find the argmax over the things
that you're interested in.
- Argmax at that moment and stick with it.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- How do you not get distracted
and switch to another thing?
- You can if you like.
- Well, if you do an argmax
repeatedly every week,
every month.
- [Andrej] Yeah, it doesn't converge.
- It's a problem.
- Yeah.
You can like low-pass filter yourself
in terms of what has
consistently been true for you.
But yeah, I definitely
see how it can be hard
but I would say you're
going to work the hardest
on the thing that you care about the most.
So low pass filter yourself
and really introspect
in your past, what are the
things that gave you energy
and what are the things that
took energy away from you?
Concrete examples.
And usually, from those concrete examples,
sometimes patterns can merge.
I like it when things look like this
when I'm in these positions.
- So that's not necessarily the field
but the kind of stuff you're
doing in a particular field.
So for you, it seems
like you were energized
by implementing stuff,
building actual things.
- Yeah, being low-level, learning
and then also communicating
so that others can go through
the same realizations
and shortening that gap.
Because I usually have
to do way too much work
to understand a thing
and then I'm like, okay,
this is actually like,
okay, I think I get it
and like why was it so much work?
It should have been much less work.
And that gives me a lot of frustration
and that's why I sometimes go teach.
- So aside from the
teaching you're doing now,
putting out videos, aside from
a potential "Godfather II"
would the AGI at Tesla and beyond,
what does the future for
Andrej Karpathy hold,
have you figured that out yet or no?
I mean as you see through the fog of war
that is all of our future, do
you start seeing silhouettes
of what that possible
future could look like?
- The consistent thing I've
been always interested in,
for me at least is Ai.
And that's probably what I'm
spending the rest of my life on
because I just care about it a lot.
And I actually care about
many other problems as well.
Like say aging, which I
basically view as disease
and I care about that as well.
But I don't think it's a good idea
to go after it, specifically.
I don't actually think
that humans will be able to
come up with the answer.
I think the correct thing to
do is to ignore those problems
and you solve AI and then use
that to solve everything else.
And I think there's a
chance that this will work.
I think it's a very high chance
and that's the way I'm betting at least.
- So when you think about AI,
are you interested in all
kinds of applications?
- [Andrej] Yes.
- All kinds of domains.
And any domain you focus on will allow you
to get insights to the big problem of AGI?
- Yeah, for me it's the
ultimate meta-problem.
I don't wanna work on
any one specific problem,
there's too many problems.
So how can you work on all
problems simultaneously?
You solve the meta-problem,
which to me is just intelligence
and how do you automate it?
- Is there cool small
projects like arxiv-sanity
and so on that you're thinking about
that ML world can anticipate.
- There's always some fun side projects.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- arxiv-sanity is one, yeah, basically,
there's way too many archive papers,
how can I organize it and
recommend papers and so on.
I transcribed all of your podcasts.
- What did you learn from that experience,
from transcribing the process of like
you consuming audiobooks
and podcasts and so on?
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- And here's a process that achieves
closer to human-level
performance on annotation.
- Yeah, well, I definitely was surprised
that transcription with OpenAI Whisper
was working so well compared
to what I'm familiar with,
from Siri and a few other systems
I guess, it works so well.
And that's what gave me
some energy to try it out.
And I thought it could be
fun to run on podcasts.
It's not obvious to me why
Whisper is so much better
compared to anything
else because I feel like
there should be a lot of incentive
for a lot of companies to
produce transcription systems
and that they've done so over a long time.
Whisper is not a super exotic
model, it's a transformer,
it takes mel spectrograms
and it just outputs tokens of text.
It's not crazy.
The model and everything has
been around for a long time.
I'm not actually a hundred
percent sure why this came about.
- Yeah, it's not obvious to me either.
It makes me feel like I'm
missing something for the middle.
- [Andrej] I'm missing something.
- Yeah, because there is a
huge, even Google and so on,
YouTube transcription.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- Yeah.
It's unclear.
But some of it is also
integrating into a bigger system.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- So the user interface, how it's deployed
and all that kind of stuff.
Maybe running it as an
independent thing is much easier,
like an order of magnitude easier
than deploying it to a
large integrated system
like YouTube transcription, or anything,
like meetings, like
Zoom has transcription,
that's kind of crappy.
But creating interface where it detects
the different individual speakers,
it's able to display
it in compelling ways,
run it real-time, all that kind of stuff.
Maybe that's difficult.
That's the only explanation I have
because I'm currently paying quite a bit
for human transcription, human caption.
- [Andrej] Right.
- Annotation.
And like it seems like
there's a huge incentive
to automate that.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- It's very confusing.
- And I think, I mean,
I dunno if you looked at
some of the Whisper transcripts,
but they're quite good.
- They're good.
And especially in tricky cases.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- I've seen Whisper's
performance on super tricky cases
and it does incredibly well.
So I don't know, a
podcast is pretty simple.
It's like high-quality audio
and you're speaking
usually pretty clearly.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- And so I don't know,
I don't know what
OpenAIs plans are either.
- But yeah, there's always
fun projects basically.
And stable diffusion also
is opening up a huge amount
of experimentation I would
say in the visual realm
and generating images, and
videos, and movies ultimately.
- [Lex] Yeah, videos now.
- And so that's going to be pretty crazy.
That's going to almost certainly work
and it's going to be really interesting
when the cost of content creation
is going to fall to zero.
You used to need a painter for
a few months to paint a thing
and now it's going to
be speak to your phone
to get your video.
- So if Hollywood will start
using that to generate scenes
which completely opens up.
Yeah.
So you can make a movie
like "Avatar" eventually
for under a million dollars.
- Much less maybe just
by talking to your phone.
I mean, I know it sounds kind of crazy.
- And then there'd be
some voting mechanism,
would there be a show on Netflix
that's generated completely automatedly?
Semi-automatedly?
- Yeah, potentially.
Yeah.
And what does it look like also
when you can just generate it on demand
and there's infinity of it?
- Yeah.
Oh, man.
All the synthetic content.
I mean it's humbling because
we treat ourselves as special
for being able to generate art,
and ideas, and all that kind of stuff.
If that can be done in
an automated way by Ai.
- Yeah.
I think it's fascinating to me how these,
the predictions of AI and
what it's going to look like
and what it's going to be capable of
are completely inverted and wrong.
And sci-fi of fifties and sixties,
were just totally not right.
They imagine AI is like super calculating,
theorem provers, and we're getting things
that can talk to you about emotions.
They can do art, it's just weird.
- Are you excited about that future?
just AI's, like hybrid
systems, heterogeneous systems
of humans and AIs talking about emotions,
Netflix and chill with an AI system.
Or the Netflix thing you
watch is also generated by AI?
- I think it's going to
be interesting for sure
and I think I'm cautiously optimistic
but it's not obvious.
- Well, the sad thing is
your brain and mine developed
in a time before Twitter,
before the internet.
So I wonder people that
are born inside of it
might have a different experience.
Like I, and maybe you will still resist it
and the people born now will not.
- Well, I do feel like humans
are extremely malleable.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And you're probably right.
- What is the meaning of life, Andrej?
We talked about the universe
having a conversation with us humans
or with the systems we
create to try to answer.
For the creator of the
universe to notice us,
we're trying to create systems
that are loud enough to answer back.
- I dunno if that's the meaning of life.
That's like meaning of
life for some people.
The first level answer I would say
is anyone can choose
their own meaning of life
because we are a conscious entity
and it's beautiful, number one.
But I do think that a
deeper meaning of life
if someone is interested
is along the lines of like,
what the hell is all this?
And like why?
And if you look into fundamental physics
and the quantum field theory
and the standard model,
they're very complicated.
And there's this 19 free
parameters of our universe
and what's going on with all
this stuff and why is it here?
And can I hack it?
Can I work with it?
Is there a message for me?
Am I supposed to create a message?
And so I think there's some
fundamental answers there
but I think there's actually even like,
you can't actually
really make dent in those
without more time.
And so to me also there's
a big question around
just getting more time, honestly.
Yeah.
That's what I think about
quite a bit as well.
- So kind of the ultimate,
or at least first way to
sneak up to the why question
is to try to escape the
system, the universe?
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- And then for that you backtrack
and say, okay, for that, that's
gonna take a very long time.
So the why question boils down
from an engineering perspective
to how do we extend?
- Yeah.
I think that's the question number one,
practically speaking, because
you're not gonna calculate
the answer to the deeper
questions in the time you have.
- And that could be
extending your own lifetime
or extending just the lifetime
of human civilization.
- Of whoever wants to, many
people might not want that.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- But I think people who do want that,
I think it's probably possible,
and I don't know that
people fully realize this.
I feel like people think of
death as an inevitability
but at the end of the day,
this is a physical system.
Some things go wrong.
It makes sense why
things like this happen,
evolutionarily speaking,
and there's most certainly
interventions that mitigate it.
- That would be interesting if
death is eventually looked at
as a fascinating thing that
used to happen to humans.
- I don't think it's unlikely.
I think it's likely.
- And it's up to our
imagination to try to predict
what the world without death looks like.
- [Andrej] Yeah.
- It's hard to, I think the
values will completely change.
- Could be, I don't really
buy all these ideas that,
oh, without death, there's no
meaning, there's nothingness.
I don't intuitively buy
all those arguments.
I think there's plenty of meaning,
plenty of things to learn.
They're interesting, exciting.
I want to know, I want to calculate,
I want to improve the
condition of all the humans
and organisms that are alive.
- Yeah.
The way we find meaning might change.
There is a lot of humans,
probably including myself,
that finds meaning in
the finiteness of things,
but that doesn't mean that's
the only source of meaning.
- Yeah.
I do think many people will go with that,
which I think is great.
I love the idea that people
can just choose their own adventure.
You are born as a conscious,
free entity by default.
I'd like to think.
- [Lex] Yeah.
- And you have your
unalienable rights for life.
- In the pursuit of happiness?
I don't know if you that, and the nature,
the landscape of happiness.
- And you can choose your
own adventure, mostly.
And that's not fully true but.
- I'm still am pretty sure I'm an NPC,
but an NPC can't know it's an NPC.
There could be different degrees
and levels of consciousness.
I don't think there's a more
beautiful way to end it.
Andrej, you're an incredible person.
I'm really honored you would talk with me,
everything you've done for
the machine learning world,
for the AI world to just inspire people,
to educate millions of people.
It's been great and I can't
wait to see what you do next.
It's been an honor, man.
Thank you so much for talking today.
- Awesome.
Thank you.
Thanks for listening to this conversation
with Andrej Karpathy,
to support this podcast
please check out our
sponsors in the description.
And now, let me leave you
some words from Samuel Karlin,
"The purpose of models
is not to fit the data
but to sharpen the questions."
Thanks for listening and
hope to see you next time.